<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine love: or The willingness of Jesus Christ to save sinners discovered in three divine dialogues, between 1. Christ and a publican. 2. Christ and a Pharisee. 3. Christ and a doubting Christian. With several other brief tracts. By V.P.</title>
            <author>Powell, Vavasor, 1617-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 144 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832345</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36818</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36818)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2053:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine love: or The willingness of Jesus Christ to save sinners discovered in three divine dialogues, between 1. Christ and a publican. 2. Christ and a Pharisee. 3. Christ and a doubting Christian. With several other brief tracts. By V.P.</title>
                  <author>Powell, Vavasor, 1617-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 278, [2] p. : ill  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for N. Crouch at the George over against the Stocks-Market,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>V.P. = Vavasor Powell.</note>
                  <note>Frontis. = ill.</note>
                  <note>"The threefold state of a Christian discovered" has a separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:36818:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>The Publican.</p>
                  <p>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</p>
                  <p>The Phariſee.</p>
                  <p>Lord I am not as other men</p>
                  <p>The doubting Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>Lord help my vnbeleefe</p>
                  <figDesc>depictions of sinners</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36818:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Divine Love: OR The willingneſs of Jeſus Chriſt To Save SINNERS; Diſcovered in three Divine Dialogues, Between
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Chriſt and a Publican.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Chriſt and a Phariſee.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Chriſt and a Doubting Chriſtian.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With ſeveral other brief Tracts.</p>
            <p>By <hi>V. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>N. Crouch</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> over againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market,</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36818:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36818:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THIS Treatiſe though ſmall in bulk, yet may be of more uſe then the many great Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of controverſy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Preſs and the World have ſo many years been tired.</p>
            <p>The method is very plain
<pb facs="tcp:36818:3"/>and familiar, by way of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>algue, though it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times much abuſed, yet may be managed to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and benefit of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as I hope this is, which is intended for the uſe of honeſt plain hearted Chriſtians, to ſhew them almoſt all (in the words of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf) his exceeding willingneſs to ſave and help poor humble repenting and returning Sinners, as alſo his reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and caſting off, of proud, ſelf conceited, and ſelf-righteous
<pb facs="tcp:36818:3"/>Phariſees and Hypocrites, who having never been ſenſible of the exceeding ſinfulneſs of Sin, do therefore never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the abſolute neceſſity of a Saviour: if any poor Soul receive the leaſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual advantage by it, I have my end in this publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>V.P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="dialogues">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36818:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36818:4"/>
                  <head>Divine Love; Diſcovered in Three Dialogues,
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Between Chriſt and a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Between Chriſt and a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Between Chriſt and a doubting Chriſtian.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <head>The firſt between Chriſt and a Publican.</head>
                     <p>IN the great day of the Feaſt, Jeſus ſtood, and cryed, ſaying, if any man thirſt, let him come to me, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.31. Then
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36818:5"/>drew near all the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Sinners for to hear him, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.1. And he ſaid unto one of them.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jeſus,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Poore Publican, what makes thee draw near to me?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Publican,</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe they ſay (Lord) that thou art a friend of Publicans &amp; Sinners, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.19.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>So I am, and thou art Welcome my beloved friend, ſit down therefore with me, and my Diſciples,</hi> Mat. 9.10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Good <hi>Maſter,</hi> though I am unworthy to come into thy preſence, yet through thy leave, I'le ſit here at thy feet, to hear
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36818:5"/>thy gracious words, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.39. <hi>John</hi> 12.3.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>How knowest thou that my words are gracious?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord I have heard thee ſay, that Publicans &amp; Harlots ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven before the Phariſees which think themſelves far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.31. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11, 12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And what ſay the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees to that?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>They murmur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, and ſay, <hi>This man receiveth ſinners, and eateth with them,</hi> Luke 15.2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Didſt thou ever hear
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36818:6"/>ine Preach beſides that time?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, once beſides, and it was the beſt, and comfortableſt <hi>Sermon</hi> that ever I heard.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Doſt thou remember a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of it?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, (though I have a bad memory, yet) I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou didſt ſay, if a man had a hundred ſheep and did looſe one of them, he would leave the ninety and nine in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and go after that which was loſt, until he find it; and when he had found it, he ſayeth it on his ſhoulders rejoycing, and when he comes home, he calleth together his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36818:6"/>friends, and neighbours, ſaying unto them, rejoyce with me, for I have found my ſheep that was loſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Is that all thou doſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>I</hi> remember ſomewhat more, that thou didſt ſpeak of a woman, that had ten pieces of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and when ſhe had loſt one piece, ſhee ſought for it till ſhe had found it, and then called her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours together to rejoyce with her. Alſo thou ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of a man that had two Sons, the one that lived ſtill at home, and was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to his Father, the other that went away from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36818:7"/>his Father, and ſpent his Fathers means among har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, till he came to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty; and yet when he returned to his Father, his Father did receive him willingly, and made him great welcome, and entertainment.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Well done my friend, thou haſt well remembred; but doſt thou know why I ſpeak theſe compariſons?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>No Sir, I do not well know that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It was to comfort, and encourage the Publicans and great ſinners, that did here me, and to ſilence the Jews that did murmur, becauſe they came to hear me, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I received them.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36818:7"/>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>It is true Lord, there were many of us there then, but we did not know what thou didſt mean by the loſt ſheep, the loſt piece, and the wicked Son.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I did mean thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, and Companions,</hi> the Publicans, Harlots, and Sinuers, <hi>that are in a loſt condition, becauſe of your Sins, and Wickedneſs in the Eyes of others (as the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees) quite loſt, and adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to periſh for ever.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But who was it Lord that did ſeek for the Loſt ſheep, and the Loſt piece of Silver?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It was I, who am</hi> the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36818:8"/>of Sinners, and the Shepherd of the ſheep, <hi>that am come to ſeek and to ſave that which is loſt,</hi> Luk. 19.10. Mat. 18.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord I am one of thoſe that are loſt, what ſhall I do to be ſaved? <hi>Act.</hi> 16.31.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I am the way, and the door, if any man enter in, he ſhall be ſaved, and whoſoever believeth on me, ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but have everlaſting life,</hi> Joh. 14.6. &amp; 10.9. &amp; 3.15.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord canſt thou ſave ſuch a Sinner as I am?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, I have power to ſave, and Power to deſtroy, but I came not to deſtroy</hi>
                           <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36818:8"/>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, the Souls of men.</note> 
                           <hi>mens lives, but to Save them,</hi> Jam. 4.12. Luk. 9.56.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>And art thou willing, Lord, that I ſhould be ſaved?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, <hi>I am willing that all ſhould be ſaved, and come to the knowledg of the truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But, Lord, I am a wicked and a ſinful man, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I know (dear Soul) thou art ſo; But, I came not to call the Righteous; but Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to Repentance,</hi> Mat. 9.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But, Lord, I am not an ordinary, but an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Sinner.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36818:9"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Notwithſtanding, poor man, hearken for thy comfort, there was a certain Creditor, that had two Debtors, the one owed five hundred pence, and the other fifty; and when they had nothing to pay, he freely forgave them both,</hi> Luk. 7.41, 42.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But, Lord, I am a greater Sinner then either of them both, for I have nothing but Sinned all my Life time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>What though, I am come to deliver thoſe that were all their life time ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to</hi>
                           <note n="(a)" place="margin">Or the bondage of Sin.</note> 
                           <hi>Bondage,</hi> Heb. 2.15.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to me being a Sinner,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36818:9"/>for <hi>I</hi> think there is not a greater ſinner upon earth then <hi>I</hi> am, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I am merciful, and I will be merciful, and will pardon thy Sins,</hi> Jer. 3.12. Heb. 8.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord, <hi>I</hi> am ſuch a Sinner, <hi>I</hi> deſerve no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for <hi>I</hi> have wearied thee with my Sins.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Though thou doſt not deſerve pardon, and though thou haſt wearied me with thy Sins, yet I will pardon thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities for my own names ſake,</hi> Eſa. 43.25.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord, <hi>I</hi> do think my Sins are ſo great, that it is impoſſible for them to be pardoned.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:36818:10"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Do not think or ſay ſo, for all things are poſſible to him that believeth,</hi> Mark 9.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But my Sins are ſo red, <hi>I</hi> think all the Water in the Sea cannot waſh them away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Though thy Sins be as Scarlet, they ſhall be as white as Snow, and though they be red like Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wool, (if thou wilt turn to me from them) for my Blood can cleanſe thee from all Sin,</hi> Eſa. 1.18. 1 John 1.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But Lord, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould turn to thee from them, yet they are written down and thou wilt not blot them out, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:36818:10"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I am he that bloteth out thy tranſgreſſions, yea, have bloted out as a thick cloud thy tranſgreſſions, and as a Cloud thy Sins; return therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, for I have redeemed thee,</hi> Eſa. 43.25. &amp; 44.22.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But if I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto thee, yet when I Sin again, thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my Sins.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No, I will pardon thee, and thy Sins and iniquities will I remember no more,</hi> Heb. 10.17.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Lord! I am the child of wicked parents, and thou haſt ſaid, thou wilt viſit the Sins of the Father, upon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to the third and fourth generation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36818:11"/>
                        <speaker>J. </speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If a wicked Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a Son, that ſeeth all his Fathers Sins which he hath done, and conſidereth and doth not ſuch like; that Son ſhall not bare the iniquity of the Father;</hi> Ezek. 18.14.20. Ezek. 16.3. to the 13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But Lord were there any wicked parents that had good Children?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, many, as wicked (a)</hi> Ahaz <hi>had good</hi> Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah; <hi>So (b) Idolutrous</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>zealous</hi> Joſiah, <hi>and ungodly</hi> Saul, <hi>had Godly</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan. <hi>(a)</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 16.20. with 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.3 <hi>(b)</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 21.21, 22. with 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22, 2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord, what if <hi>I</hi> be a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36818:11"/>Baſtard, and the Child of whoredom?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That doth not hinder thee neither to be ſaved, for my ſervant (c)</hi> Jeptha <hi>was a Baſtard; ſo was my ſervant</hi> Phares <hi>who is reckoned in my own Genealogie.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Gen. 38.18. &amp; 29. &amp; Ruth 4.12. with Mat. 1.3. <hi>(c)</hi> Jud. 11.1. with Heb. 11.32.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But Lord, is there not ſuch a Scripture, that a Baſtard ſhall not enter into thy Congregation until the tenth Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes there is ſuch a (d) Scripture, and that ſhould make People ſhun the Sin of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36818:12"/>Whoredome, but that doth not exclude men that are born Baſtards after the Fleſh, if they be Born again of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, either out of my Church on Earth, (now in the days of the Goſpel) or yet out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> Deut. 23.2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But what Lord, if my Father was a Baſtard?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Neither doth that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for</hi> Sarah <hi>the brother of</hi> Phares <hi>(who was a Baſtard) begot my two wiſe and Godly Servants</hi> Ethan <hi>and</hi> Heman, compare Gen. 38.30. 1 Chron. 26. with Pſal. 88. and Pſal. 89. the titles of both being of <hi>Heman,</hi> and <hi>Ethan.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36818:12"/>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Lord, I am a very old Sinner, and have one foot already in the Grave, and I fear it is too late for me now to be called.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No, it is not too late, for I call ſome at the ninth hour, yea ſome at the (e) ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth hour.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Which is but one hour before night, or a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death.</note> 
                           <hi>And I will pour out of my Spirit upon old men in theſe Goſpel daies,</hi> Mat. 20.6.9. Joel 2.28. with Act. 2.17.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But Lord, I have committed ſuch great and hainous Sins, both by ſpeaking and doing, that I am affraid it is in vain for me to ſeek Mercy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:36818:13"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Though thou haſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and done evil things, as much as thou couldeſt, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto me,</hi> and I will not cauſe mine anger to fall upon thee, for I am mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>How ſhall I look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, <hi>Gracious Lord,</hi> for I have multiplied ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As thou haſt multiplied ſin, ſo will I</hi>
                           <note n="(f)" place="margin">Or will abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pardon.</note> 
                           <hi>multiply pardons, if thou wilt return unto me the Lord,</hi> Eſa. 55.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh but Lord, I ſcarce think that any ſo wicked as my ſelf were ſaved, for I was an <hi>Idolater,</hi> an <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer,</hi>
                           <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36818:13"/>a <hi>Thief,</hi> a <hi>Drunkard,</hi> and what not that was wicked.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Such were many of my ſervants that are now in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but I according to my own kindneſs, and pitty to them, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them by</hi> waſhing, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying <hi>and</hi> juſtifying <hi>them, by my own</hi>
                           <note n="(g)" place="margin">Or power</note> 
                           <hi>Name, Blood, and Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.6, 9, 10, 11. Tit. 3.3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh but merciful Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, I was a Ring-leader of others into ſin, and I enticed, and drew many into wickedneſs, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my caſe is far worſe then others.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As thou waſt a</hi> Ring-leader,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36818:14"/>
                           <hi>and</hi> Enticer <hi>of others into ſin, ſo I can make thee a</hi> guide <hi>and</hi> leader <hi>of others into, and in the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, as I made thy Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Levi <hi>and others.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But that which makes me fear moſt, is becauſe I was a <hi>Blaſphemer, Reviler,</hi> and <hi>Perſecuter</hi> of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yea many of thy Saints, did I ſhut up in Priſon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yet thou ſhalt have mercy, becauſe thou didst it ignorantly, through unbeliefe,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh but Lord, I finde my heart is hardened, through the deceitfulneſs and cuſtome of ſin, that I cannot hope it will ever be otherwiſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:36818:14"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I can and will take the ſtony heart out of thy fleſh, and I will give thee a heart of fleſh,</hi> Eze. 36.26.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord wilt thou do all for me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I muſt do all for thee, for without me thou canſt do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> Phil. 2.13. Joh. 15.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P</speaker>
                        <p>Lord, what then ſhall I do?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Before I teach thee what thou muſt do, I will firſt ſhew thee, what I have done, and ſuffered for thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Good Maſter I deſire to know that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p n="1">1. I left my own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and came into the world to ſave thee, and ſuch ſinners as thou art,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36818:15"/>
                           <hi>John</hi> 17.5. 1 Tim. 1.15.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Though <hi>I</hi> was the onely Son of my Father, and in his own form, and equal to him; yet <hi>I</hi> took upon me the form of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, for thee and thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſake, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Though <hi>I</hi> was Heire of all things, and Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Heaven and Earth, yet <hi>I</hi> became poor and hungary, that thou might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be made rich, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.19. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Though <hi>I</hi> deſerved honour, and glory; yet <hi>I</hi> was reviled, threatned, and perſcuted by my own Creatures, and all for my
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36818:15"/>good will to thee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.23.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Though <hi>I</hi> had no ſin, yet <hi>I</hi> was made ſin that thou poor ſinner mighteſt eſcape ſin, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. and 2.22. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. Though <hi>I</hi> was a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, and Law-maker, yet <hi>I</hi> became under the curſe of my own Law, that <hi>I</hi> might redeem thee from that curſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. When <hi>I</hi> had power over mine own life, and no man could take it from me, yet <hi>I</hi> laid it down for thee, that thou mighteſt have life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6.9. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                        <p n="8">
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36818:16"/>8. Though <hi>I</hi> was my fathers delight, and an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his love from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, yet <hi>I</hi> became an object of his wrath, for my love to thee, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.30. Pſa. 88.16. &amp; 102.10.</p>
                        <p n="9">9. When thou waſt an enemy, and ſtranger to God my Father, <hi>I</hi> made peace between him and thee, and reconciled thee to him by my death, and ſufferings, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20.21. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12, 13.</p>
                        <p n="10">10. When thou wert a ſlave to the Devil, and a fire-brand of Hell; <hi>I</hi> did reſcue thee from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the one, and redeem thee from the plague and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36818:16"/>punniſhment of the other, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Amos.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Lord <hi>I</hi> did not deſerve any of this from thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>True thou didſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, but yet I did it freely, and out of my love to thee,</hi> Rom. 3.24. Eph. 5.2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Are all my ſins, Lord, ſatisfied for, and done a way by thy death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, they are perfectly ſatisfied for, and abſolutely done away out of my fathers ſight, never to be imputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to thee,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.19.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>And is there nothing now in the way that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders me to be ſaved?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36818:17"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No, there is nothing, for I have taken all things out of the way, that hindred thee to be ſaved,</hi> Col. 2.14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>And am <hi>I</hi> to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſaved?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No nothing at all towards thy own ſalvation, for I have bought thee from death, and purchaſed thee life, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.20. 1 Pet. 1.18, 19. Eph. 1.14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Shall <hi>I</hi> then be ſaved Lord?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, if thou wilt believe, and truſt wholly and only upon me, and upon my righteouſneſs and merits, thou ſhalt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> Joh. 3.36. Rom. 9.33. and Rom. 10.9.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord <hi>I</hi> would believe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36818:17"/>but <hi>I</hi> partly am afraid to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and partly I am ſo weak <hi>I</hi> cannot believe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou poor fearful heart, fear not, but be ſtrong,</hi> Eſa. 35.4. <hi>But tell me why thou are afaid.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Leaſt I ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, or leaſt I ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and have no ground for my faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It is not preſumption for thee to do what I command thee, but it is obedience, and is not my word of promiſe a ſufficient ground for thy faith?</hi> 1 Joh. 3.23. Joh. 5.24.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Doeſt thou then Lord command me to believe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, fear not, believe on me, and thou ſhalt be ſaved,</hi>
                           <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36818:18"/>Lu. 8.50. with Act. 16.31.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But Lord though thou commandeſt me, yet <hi>I</hi> have no power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I will write my Laws in thy heart, and will inable and give thee power to believe,</hi> Heb. 8.10. Mat. 12.21.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord if thou wilt alſo give me power to believe, <hi>I</hi> will acknowledg I am nothing, but what I am in thee; and that <hi>I</hi> have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what <hi>I</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Doeſt thou not believe?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh yes, now Lord I do believe, Joh. 9.38.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>This is the work and gift of God that thou doeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36818:18"/>for fleſh and blood hath not wrought this in thee,</hi> Joh. 6.29. Eph. 2.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Lord, I do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg it to be thy work, but I am afraid I ſhall looſe this faith again.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I that am the Authour of thy faith, will alſo finiſh it: be therefore of good chear, for thou art one of my Fathers children, and of my Saints, and my ſpirit ſhall abide in thee for ever,</hi> Heb. 12.2. Joh. 1.12. Joh. 4.14. John 7.38, 39.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord I have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Father, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and <hi>I</hi> am unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be called either his Son or thy Servant, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.21.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36818:19"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Son thy ſins are forgiven thee, ſin no more,</hi> Luk. 5.23. John 8.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord <hi>I</hi> am afraid <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſin again, though <hi>I</hi> deſire, and reſolve never to do it. But what Lord, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſin againſt my will?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou canſt not ſin wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and wilfully; for my ſeed of grace will remain in thee, and if thou ſinneſt through weakeneſs, and frailty, I will be an Advocate, propitiation for thy ſins,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.9. 1 Joh. 2.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it then thy will Lord, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould have forgiveneſs of my ſins, and doubt no more?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:36818:19"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes ſure, for theſe things have I ſpoken, that thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have a full aſſurance, and doubt no more.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But what if Sathan, when he ſees me ſin, will tempt me to doubt again?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Say unto him, that I am faithful and juſt to forgive thee thy ſins, and that my blood cleanſeth thee from all ſin,</hi> 1 Joh. 17.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But Lord wilt not thou have me to confeſs my ſins?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, I will have thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs them, and forſake them,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.9. Prov. 28.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>But Lord, is it thy mind, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould always be ſorrowful?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:36818:20"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No, but it is my mind, rather that thou ſhouldeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rejoyce, and have ſtrong conſolation,</hi> Phil. 4.4. Heb. 6.18.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Lord, <hi>I</hi> cannot chuſe but cry, and mourn, and be aſhamed, and hate my ſelf for all my former wickedneſs, and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.61.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou maieſt do that, and yet hold faſt thy confidence; for the ſpirit of mourning, and the ſpirit of grace and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may be in thy heart at once, and the one not deſtroy the other,</hi> Zac. 12.10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Lord how is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou maiſt mourn at the ſight of thy ſins, as they were
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36818:20"/>committed against me, and for thy denying, felling, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying me, and yet thou maieſt believe (becauſe I have ſaid ſo) that they are all pardoned. As</hi> Joſephs <hi>brethren cryed, and complained for their guiltineſs in ſelling him, yet they were glad that he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, and could help them in their diſtreſs,</hi> Gen. 42.21, 22.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>Now Lord thou haſt taught me what <hi>I</hi> ſhould do in reſpect of my ſelf, but now Lord <hi>I</hi> would do ſomething for thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Come then and follow me,</hi> Mat. 9, 9. <hi>And be aroſe and followed him.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:36818:21"/>
                     <head>The ſecond Conference between Chriſt, and a Phariſee.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phariſee.</speaker>
                        <p>THen one of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees came to him, and asked him, what ſhall <hi>I</hi> do to work the work of God, <hi>John.</hi> 6.28.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jeſus.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>This is the work of God, that thou believe in him</hi> (viz. me) <hi>whom he hath ſent,</hi> Joh. 6.29.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>But Maſter what good thing ſhall <hi>I</hi> do that <hi>I</hi> may have eternal life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:36818:21"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If thou wilt be ſaved by doing, then keep the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I have kept them all from my youth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19, 20.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Then thou art no ſinner.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, we are all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but <hi>I</hi> thank God <hi>I</hi> am not as other men are, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners, Unjuſt, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, or even as this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Why, what doeſt thou more than this Publican?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> faſt twice in the week, and give tithes of all that <hi>I</hi> poſſeſs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Law, <hi>I</hi> live blameleſs, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36818:22"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Hast thou never read that they which followed after the Law of Righteouſneſs, have not attained to the Law of Righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 9.31.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>I</hi> never obſerved that, but I remember ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther text, where God ſaith, I gave them my Satutes, and ſhewed them my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which if a man do, he ſhall live in them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Daeſt thou think to go to heaven by doing?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Not by doing only, but by doing good, and departing from evil.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But doth not the Law ſay, curſed is he that obſerveth not all things that are written
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36818:22"/>in the words of the Law to do them,</hi> Deut. 27.26.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, that is, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever breaks the Law is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, unleſs he repents for it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The Law doth not ſay, unleſs men repent for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it they are accurſed, but it ſays abſolutely they are curſed, and I ſay, whoſoever keepeth the whole law and yet offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in one point, he is guilty of all,</hi> Gal. 3.10. Jam. 2.10. Mat. 5.19.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſay ſo too, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept men keep the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> they (<hi>a</hi>) cannot be ſaved, and whoſoever (<hi>b</hi>) know not, and keep not the Law, they are accurſed.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36818:23"/>Acts 15.1.24. Joh. 7.49</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Doeſt thou know the Law</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, I know the Law for I am inſtructed daily out of the Law, by our (<hi>c</hi>) Doctors of the Law and holy Prieſts, (<hi>c</hi>) <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.4.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The Priests have done violence to the Law, and they that (d) handle the Law know not the Lord, (d) Jer.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Jehovah,</hi> hath ſaid, that the Law ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh from the Prieſts, for the Prieſts lips is to keep knowledg, and we are to ſeek the Law at his mouth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18: 18. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>God hath ſaid alſo, that the Law ſhall (c) periſh from the Prieſts, and that they (f)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36818:23"/>ſhall not every man teach his neighbour any more, for all ſhall know the Lord, from the leaſt to the greatest,</hi> Jer. 31.4.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I perceive thou goeſt about to deſtroy the Law.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Think not ſo, for I am not come to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfil it,</hi> Mat. 5.17. Luke 16.17.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I Sir, I like that, that we ſhould fulfil the Law, that we ſhould perform it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes,</hi> Moſes <hi>gave you the Law, but (a) none of you keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, but (b) you have been partial in the Law. (c) Ye pay tithe of Mint, Annis, and Cumming, and have omitted the weightier matters of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36818:24"/>Law, Judgment, Mercy, and Faith,</hi> Joh. 7.19. Mal. 2.9. Mat. 23.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>P.</speaker>
                        <p>It is true, we may come ſhore in ſome things, but he that keepeth the Law happy is he.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou that (d) reſteſt in the Law, and makeſt thy boaſt of the Law, through breaking the Law thou doeſt diſhonour God, and cauſeſt many to (f) ſtumble at the Law, verily I ſay unto thee, thou (g) ſhalt be judged by the Law,</hi> Rom. 2.17. <hi>ver.</hi> 23. Mal. 2.8. Rom. 2.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>No, I hope rather to be juſtified, then to be judged by the Law.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36818:24"/>thee, by the deeds of the Law, there ſhall no fleſh be juſtified in God: ſight,</hi> Rom. 3.20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Gal. 3.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>How then ſhall I be juſtified?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The righteouſneſs of God without the Law is manifeſt, being witneſſed by the Law and the Prophets,</hi> Rom. 3.21.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>What Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Not a mans</hi> (h) <hi>own righteouſneſs, which is called, the</hi> (i) <hi>righteouſneſs of the Law; but the</hi> (k) <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which is of God by faith (h)</hi> Phil. 3.9. (<hi>i</hi>) Ro. 2.26. (<hi>k</hi>) Ro. 4.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>What difference is there between the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36818:25"/>of the Law, and the righteouſneſs of faith?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>Moſes <hi>deſcribeth the righteouſneſs of the Law,</hi> thus <hi>that the man which doth thoſe things which the Law requireth ſhall live by them; but the righteouſneſs of faith, ſaith, whoſoever believeth on me ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Rom. 10.5.6, 11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>How can men be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by believing in thee, for thou art but one?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>As by one</hi> (l) <hi>mans of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence death reigned, by one muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap> they which receive abundance of grace, and of the gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> righteouſneſs, ſhall reign in life by me. Who am the</hi> (m) <hi>Son of righteouſneſs,</hi> (n) <hi>and made by God my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36818:25"/>to be righteouſneſs unto men. (l)</hi> Rom. 5.7. (<hi>m</hi>) Mal. 4.2. [<hi>n</hi>] 1 Cor. 1.30.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou beareſt record of thy ſelf, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>[o] <hi>Though I bear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of my ſelf, yet my record is true.</hi> [p] <hi>My Father alſo beareth witneſs of me, and this is his witneſs, that he hath given life, and this life is in [me] his Son. [o]</hi> Joh. 8.14. [<hi>p</hi>] 1 Joh. 5.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>But what ſay'ſt thou, how was our Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his ſeed [who liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before thee] juſtified and ſaved?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>[q] <hi>Your Father</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>rejoyced to ſee my day, and he ſaw it, and was glad,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36818:26"/>for</hi> [l] <hi>I was before</hi> Abraham <hi>and he and his ſpiritual ſeed, were justified and ſaved by faith in me.</hi> (<hi>r</hi>) Rom. 4.3.11, 13, 16. Gal. 3.14.18.20.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>But was not <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> juſtified by works?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If</hi> Abraham <hi>were juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by works, be hath whereof to glory, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; for what ſaith the Scripture,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">It is true <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith was accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with works.</note> Abraham <hi>believed God, and it was accounted to him for Righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 4.2.3.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>If I be not juſtified by my good works, to what end ſhould I perform them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:36818:26"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Though thy good works cannot juſtifie thee before God, yet they may glorifie God, and be prafitable unto men,</hi> Mat. 5.16. Tit. 3.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Well then, I am glad my good works be good for ſomething.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, thy good works would be good for ſomething, if thy faith like</hi> Abrahams) <hi>did work with thy works, but thou doeſt not believe, and all thy good works thou doeſt to be ſeen of men,</hi> Jam. 2.22. Mat. 23.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>No, I do not do my good works to be ſeen of men, but to pleaſe God.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I tell thee, that</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith it is impoſſible
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36818:27"/>to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>But God hath ſaid, if a man do well, he ſhall be accepted.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It is not for their well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing that men are accepted with my Father, but they are made acceptable in me, and their works are accepted for my ſake,</hi> Eph. 1.6. 1 Pet. 2.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>But am I no nearer Heaven, that perform good works, than this finfull and ungodly Publican?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou Hypocrite that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiest thy ſelf, and judgeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, I tell thee, that Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Harlots ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven before ſuch as thou art,</hi> Mat. 7.5. and 21, 31.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36818:27"/>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh untrue, and falſe doctrine, to ſay, that thoſe curſed men who know not the Law, ſhould be ſaved before us, who are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Joh. 7.49. &amp; 8.33.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou blind, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceited</hi> Phariſee, <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt thou not the Scripture?</hi> I will have mercy, and not ſacrifice, for I am not come to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance. <hi>And I ſay unto thee, unleſs thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt believe in mee, thou art not the child of</hi> Abraham, Mat. 9.13. Gal. 3.26.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> believe in the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the God of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> and the God of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi>
                           <pb n="48" facs="tcp:36818:28"/>whoſe child and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant I am.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If thou didſt believe in God, thou wouldeſt alſo believe in me, but thou art the child of the Devil, and in bondage to this day,</hi> Joh. 8.44. Gal. 4.25.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>How am I in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou art under the curſe of the Law, and under the power of ſin and Sathan; and canſt never be made free, unleſs I make thee free,</hi> Joh. 8.34, 35, 36.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>How doeſt thou free men?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>By my (a) death and ſufferings, I ſatisfie the Law; by the (b) power of my reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36818:28"/>I overcome death; and by my Spirit I (m) caſt out Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and (n) ſubdue ſin, (a)</hi> Gal. 3.13. (<hi>b</hi>) 1 Cor. 15.55.57. (<hi>m</hi>) Mat 12.28. (<hi>n</hi>) Rom. 8.2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I hope to be freed another way, to wit, by my ſacrifices, prayers, and good works.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thy ſacrifices and thy prayers, are an abomination unto me, and thy workes are not found perfect before God,</hi> Eſa. 66.3. Prov. 15.8. and 28.9. Rev. 3.2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>What doſt thou think to beat me off from my long prayers, and good works? I hope by theſe, together with my faſting,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36818:29"/>and mourning, to lay a ſure, and happy foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for my ſoul, for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou worker of iniquity, that doſt (a) practice bypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, I tell thee thy prayers are (b) ſin, thy works are done to be ſeen of men; thou alſo faſteſt for (c) ſtrife, and thy mourning is but hypocritical: therefore inſtead of laying a ſure and happy foundation, thou (d) heapeſt up wrath to thy ſelf, againſt the day of wrath,</hi> (<hi>a</hi>) Eſa. 32.6. (<hi>b</hi>) Pſ. 109.7. (<hi>c</hi>) Eſ. 58.4.5. (<hi>d</hi>) Job. 36.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I am not a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, but a true child of God, and I hope I ſhall belived, for I know moſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36818:29"/>good men take me for a godly and righteous man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Though thou doſt cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly (e) appear righteous unto men, yet within thou art full of hypocriſie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity; thou ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, thy (f) hope will periſh, for thou canſt not (g) eſcape the damnation of hell,</hi> (<hi>e</hi>) Mat. 23.28. (<hi>f</hi>) Job. 8.13. (<hi>g</hi>) Mat. 23.33.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I do not fear what thou ſayeſt, for I am better perſwaded of my ſelf.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Though thy ſcared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and hardned heart hinders the yet from fearing; yet fear, terrour, and trembling ſhall (h) ſurpriſe, and fill thy ſpirit, that thou ſhalt roare in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36818:30"/>(i) flame; of fire, and in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting burnings,</hi> (<hi>h</hi>) Eſ. 33.14. Deut. 32.22. (<hi>i</hi>) Luk. 3.17. Mark. 9.43.44, 46.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I have joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in my ſpirit often from my performances, and I know that God will hear my prayers, that I make publickly and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately unto him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou painted Sepulchre, baſt thou not read! that the (k) joy of an hypacrite is but for a moment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> and that an hypocrite ſhall not (l) come before God, And doſt thou not (m) reſtrain prayer before God; and when thou praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t, doſt thou not do it publickly to be (n) ſeen of men? (k)</hi> Job.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36818:30"/>20.5 (<hi>l</hi>) Job. 13.16. (<hi>m</hi>) Job. 15.4. (<hi>n</hi>) Mat. 6.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> pray in private alſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Then it is either when (o) ſome puniſhment is upon thee, or elſe to quiet thy car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal conſcience, (s)</hi> Eſa 26.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Mr. why doſt thou reproach me in ſaying thus?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou diſſembler that (p) ſeekeſt honour of men, and not the honour which commeth from God: thou art to expect nothing but ſhame, and (q) everlaſting contempt. (p)</hi> Joh. 5.44. (<hi>q</hi>) Dan. 12.2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, thou judgeſt raſhly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:36818:31"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No, as I hear, I judge, and my judgment is juſt and true,</hi> Joh. 5.30. and 8.16.26.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>How knoweſt thou what I am, that thou ſo judgeſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I am he that ſearcheth the heart and trieth the reines, and I will give to every one of you according to your works,</hi> Rev. 2.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>When thou judgeſt the world, what difference wilt thou make between us that ſerve God, and the Heathens that ſerved him not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The difference will be this, that your [r] condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be the greater, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36818:31"/>though ye know God, yet ye ſerved him [s] vainly, falſly, and [t] hypocritically. (r)</hi> Mat. 23.14. Mar. 12.40. Luk. 20.47. <hi>(s)</hi> Mat. 15.9. <hi>(t)</hi> Eſa. 57.4.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Good Maſter, I would eſcape this condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, for I believe it will be great, and thy words begin to terrifie me already.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I have told thee already, that there is no other way for thee to eſcape it, but only by me, but yet thou doſt not believe me,</hi> Joh. 10.25.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>How wilt thou have me believe in thee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt, I will have thee ſee thy ſelfe to be the (v) great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36818:32"/>and vilest of ſinners, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> thy [u] own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſervice, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, to be as filthy and me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ruous rags: And after thou haſt denied and (w) ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred thy ſelfe, then cry out, Maſter, ſave me, or elſe I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; for the (x) whole need not a Phyſitian, but thoſe that are ſick, (v)</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>(u)</hi> Eſa. 64.6 <hi>(w)</hi> Eze. 36.31. <hi>[x]</hi> Mat. 9.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe ſee my ſelf a ſinner, and I am ſorry for my ſins. And doth nor God ſay, <hi>that whoſoever confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſins ſhall find mercy.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I ſay unto thee (thou luke-warm Profeſſor) Except
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36818:32"/>thou eateſt my fleſh, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my blood; and ſubmitteſt unto my righteouſneſs, thou canſt not be ſaved,</hi> Joh. 6.53.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Well then; If I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaved by my own works, and righteouſneſs, Maſter, let me be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thee to ſave me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Haſt thou not read, that (a) Salvation belongeth onely to the Lord, and that men are ſaved by grace, without the works of the Law; why then doſt thou ſo (b) lightly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of the Rock of thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? by ſeeking to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſaved (as (c) it were) by thy own works: I tell thee again, thou muſt (d)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36818:33"/>deny thy own righteouſneſs wholly, and look to be found in my righteouſneſs only, elſe thou canſt not be ſaved (a)</hi> Pſal. 3.8. <hi>(b)</hi> Deut. 32.15. <hi>(c)</hi> Rom. 9.32 <hi>(d)</hi> Phil. 3.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>Indeed Maſter, thou makeſt the way to Heaven very hard.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It is ſo hard, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall ſeek to enter in, and ſhall not be able,</hi> Luke 13.24.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>If it be as thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. I am afraid that many of our beſt Scribes and Phariſees will come ſhort of Heaven.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou maiſt be ſure of that, for verily I ſay unto thee,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36818:33"/>Except thy righteouſneſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, thou ſhalt in no eaſe enter into the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 5.20.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>But Maſter, there be ſome that do great works in thy name, ſhall not all ſuch be ſaved?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No, for many will ſay unto me hereafter,</hi> Lord, Lord, <hi>have we not propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in thy Name, and in thy name cast out devils, and in thy name done many wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things; and then will I profeſs unto them, I never knew you,</hi> depart from me ye workers of iniquity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:36818:34"/>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>But why ſhould not ſuch rather be ſaved then caſt away?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Becauſe they did [as thou doſt] d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſe things to be ſeen of men, and to gain honour unto themſelves, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> built their Salvation upon this falſe foundation, as the fooliſh builder built his houſe upon the ſand, which in</hi>
                           <note n="[g]" place="margin">
                              <hi>i. e.</hi> Times of Trial and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. Luke 8.12.</note> 
                           <hi>time of flood, and wind, could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>and, but fell,</hi> Mat. 7.26, 27.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſee thou doſt reject me, I thought to be one of thy Diſciples, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:36818:34"/>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No, I do not reject thee, but am very willing to receive thee; but firſt conſider, what thou doſt, and what it will coſt, thee, if thou wilt be my Diſciple, and follow me.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>What will it coſt me Maſter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>J.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou muſt</hi>
                           <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                              <hi>i. e.</hi> In compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of Chriſt, and when they come in competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him. Mat. 10.37.</note> 
                           <hi>hate thy father and mother &amp; wife and Children, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſiſters, and thine own life alſo; yea thou muſt go, and ſell all that thou haſt, and take up thy croſſe daily, and follow me, elſe thou canſt not be my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi> Luke 14.26, 27.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:36818:35"/>
                        <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                        <p>This is a hard ſaying, who can hear it, and he went away ſorrowful, and followed him no more, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.60.66. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.22.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:36818:35"/>
                     <head>The third Conference between Chriſt, and a doubting Chriſtian.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                        <p>COme unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh Lord I am a poor heavy laden ſinner that would come unto thee, but cannot come.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>It is true O ſoul, no man can come unto me, except the Father which hath ſent me draw him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:36818:36"/>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>How then Lord ſhall I come unto thee?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I and my Father are one, and we give pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the faint, and to them that have no might, we add ſtrength, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.30 <hi>Eſay</hi> 40, 29.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>Lord, <hi>I am altogether without ſtrength therefore draw me unto thee and I will come.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I will draw thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me with the cords o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> a man, with bands of love and with loving kindneſs, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> I look upon my ſelfe, I ſee I am unworthy to come unto thee
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36818:36"/>yea, unworthy of the leaſt of thy mercies.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So ſaid my ſervant <hi>(a) John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>(b) Jacob,</hi> and <hi>(c)</hi> others, yet do not judge thy ſelſe (as the <hi>(d)</hi> Jewes did) unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of eternal life, <hi>(a) Mat.</hi> 3.11.6. <hi>(b) Gen.</hi> 32.10. <hi>(c) Luk.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.8. <hi>(d) Acts</hi> 13.46.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> ſuch men as</hi> John Baptiſt, <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>did judge themſelves unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; how many thouſand times more unworthy am I, a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and wicked ſinner?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>It is true, neither <hi>they,</hi> nor <hi>thou,</hi> could be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your ſelves, but yet I am willing to account
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36818:37"/>you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,<note place="margin">As the prodi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gals Father did his Son, Luk. 15.21, 22.</note> 
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35. and 21.36, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.4.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſti.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord, if ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> were any thing that were good in me, it might a little incou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage me to come unto thee, but I find nothing but evil in me.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Doſt thou not know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> that without me thou canſt <hi>(e)</hi> do nothing; and that a man can <hi>(f)</hi> receive no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, except it be give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> him from heaven. Why the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> doſt thou ſtay away from me who muſt <hi>(g)</hi> work all thy workes in thee And, <hi>(c) Joh.</hi> 15.5. <hi>(f) Joh.</hi> 3.27. <hi>(g) Eſa.</hi> 26.12 2, 12.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <pb n="67" facs="tcp:36818:37"/>2. Becauſe thou ſeeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but evil in thee, thou ſhouldſt thee rather come unto me, who am the <hi>(h)</hi> Fountain wherein thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſoul muſt be waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and unleſs I <hi>(i)</hi> waſh <hi>thee</hi> thou canſt not be clean, nor have any <hi>(k)</hi> part in me, <hi>(h) Zac</hi> 13.1. <hi>(i) Eze.</hi> 36.25. and 1.9. <hi>(k) Joh.</hi> 13.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>True Lord, thou art the</hi> Fountain <hi>and</hi> wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring <hi>of life, and it is thy blood (and nothing elſe) that can waſh a way my ſins: but how can I come near to thee, who am ſo wicked, that for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ught I know, have counted thy blood an (l) unholy thing, (l)</hi> Heb. 10.29.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:36818:38"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou poor, dear, and doubting ſoul, what if thou hadſt had a hand in crucifying me (as the Jewes had?) yet cannot I forgive thee, as I did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them. But thou haſt not counted my blood an unholy thing, for thou ſtill deſireſt to have thy ſins waſhed away by it, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36.41.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>What the Jewes did, they did ignorantly; but I have ſinned againſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which makes my ſins worſe then theirs.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>If thou haſt ſinned againſt knowledge, ye thou haſt not ſinned ſo but that thou maiſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36818:38"/>For my dear Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Peter</hi> ſinned againſt knowledg, when he denied with an oath that he knew me not, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.72.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but yet my ſins are worſe then his, for his ſin was but one ſin, and that a ſuddain and ſhort ſin; but I have ſinned many ſins and continued long in them.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So did my beloved ſervant <hi>David</hi> (who was a man according to my own heart) commit ſeveral ſins together, as <hi>Murther, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp;c.</hi> and continued a while too in his ſins.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but Lord, thoſe ſervants of thine though they ſinned againſt thee yet
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36818:39"/>they expreſſed a great deal of ſence of their ſins, and ſorrow for them; but I can neither be ſenſible of, nor ſorrowful for mine.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh ſweet ſoul, thou miſtakeſt, and forgetteſt thy ſelfe, for thou doſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten confeſs thy ſins before me with <hi>ſence, ſhame,</hi> and <hi>ſorrow.</hi> And I hear the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bemoaning, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, and ſaying, <hi>I have (n) ſinned againſt the Lord, woe is me for I am undone, (n)</hi> Job. 7 20. Pſal. 51.4. Lam. 5.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh good Lord, it is not without a cauſe that I cry</hi> woe is me I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; <hi>for I think there is no
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36818:39"/>ſoul in ſuch a dangerous, and deſperate condition, as mine is in.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Why doeſt thou think, and ſay ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Becauſe I have ſinned that unpardonable ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſpirit.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh thou poor and precious ſoul, thou doſt but think ſo, and fear ſo: But tell me how canſt thou ſin that ſin againſt my <hi>Spirit,</hi> and yet pray for more of my <hi>Spirit,</hi> and ſo much prize my <hi>Spirit</hi> as thou doſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Lord, <hi>I have often grieved and quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy</hi> Spirit, <hi>and is not this to commit that unpardonable ſin?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:36818:40"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>My own dear and loving children may and do ſometimes grieve my ſpirit by ſining and quench the gracious motions of it and yet do not ſin that unpardonable ſin, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.10.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>nk no leſs, but that I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                                 <desc>•••••</desc>
                              </gap>red that ſin, for I have had</hi> hard, cruel and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>thoughts in my heart, againſt the Holy Spirit.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Though (my child) tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> haſt had ſuch <hi>thoughts</hi> in thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, yet thou haſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>oken evil of my <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> (as the Jewes did) which is the ſin of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36818:40"/>and that unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſin, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.24, 28, 31. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.22, to 30.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord I am not ſure but that I have ſpoken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil words of thy ſpirit; for I know I have many times utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> vile, bitter, <hi>and</hi> curſed <hi>words.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Notwithſtanding, thou dideſt through the violence of thy temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and in the bitterneſs of thy Soul ſpeak ſuch words (as my ſervants <hi>Job, David, Jeremy, Jonah,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> did) yet thou haſt not done deſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully (nor ſinned malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and wilfully) againſt my Spirit of grace as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36818:41"/>doe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Job.</hi> 3. to 13. and 10.18. and 23.15, 16. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 31.22. and 116.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.14, &amp;c. <hi>Jonah.</hi> 4.3, 4, 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26, 27, 74.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh I have been and ſtill am very wilful, and have often ſinned wilfully, and thou ſayeſt in thy word, that if any ſin wilfully after they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the knowledge of the truth their remaineth no more ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſins, Heb.</hi> 10.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou dear ſoul, have not I heard thee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in prayer complaining of, and bewailing thy ſins, and beging earneſtly for power againſt them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is rather againſt thy
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36818:41"/>will (then wilfully) that thou doſt ſin.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but I find ſins in power in my ſoul, which if I were a Saint they would not be ſo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>My ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Paul</hi> found ſin ſo ſtrong in him that he confeſſed he was carnal,<note place="margin">Sin was in power in <hi>Paul</hi> when it could carry him captive.</note> and ſold under ſin; and that he found a law in his members, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the law of his mind, and bringing him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captivity to the law of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but neither</hi> Paul <hi>nor any other</hi> Saint, <hi>hath ſinned preſumptuouſly as I have done.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:36818:42"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>My ſervant <hi>David</hi> pray'd, that he might be kept from preſumptuous ſins, for he was ſubject there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,<note place="margin">Pſ. 19.13. It is probable that <hi>David</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in kiling <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah.</hi>
                           </note> and ſo are the beſt of my Saints.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſti.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord I have rebelled against thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So did my ſervants of ‖ old, but I have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ‖ gifts for the <hi>Rebellious,</hi> and to me belongs mercies and forgiveneſs, though thou haſt rebelled againſt me, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9 9 ‖ <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.2. and 63.20. ‖ <hi>Iſ</hi> 68.18.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but my</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion <hi>is the worſt</hi> Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:36818:42"/>
                           <hi>of all, for I have rebelled againſt the light; I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed thee, and yet I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied thee, and made an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical profeſſion; I ſeemed like</hi> Judas, <hi>to be thy friend, whilſt in my heart I did not love thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>The houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> dealt treacherouſly againſt me the Lord, and belied me, and <hi>Ephraim</hi> my dear Son, compaſſed me about with lies, yet was I graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.11.12. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.12. with <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6. and 31.20.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim <hi>was never ſo wicked as I am, and guilty of ſuch
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:36818:43"/>Lukewarmneſs, Hypocriſie and Backſliding as I am guilty of.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Yea, <hi>Ephraim</hi> was a cake not turned. And <hi>Ephraim</hi> fed upon winds and provoked me to anger moſt bitterly, yet my bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els did ſtill worke toward <hi>Ephraim,</hi> that I could not deſtroy him <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.8. and 12.1.14. with 11.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But I increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſin, and the more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies I received, the more my heart was exalted.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Even ſo did <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſin more and more, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as he was filled, ſo his heart was exalted, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.2, 6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord what
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36818:43"/>didſt thou do to</hi> Ephraim?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I drew them with the cords of man, and with bands of love, and I was as the dew unto them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. and 14.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but I have forſaken the Lord, and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlided from thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So did <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, Jer.</hi> 2, 13. and 3.6. and 4.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord I find that my heart is bent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual backſliding, yea, my bak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings are encreaſed.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So were ‖ they yet I healed their backſlidings, ſo will I heal thine alſo, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14.22. ‖ <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:36818:44"/>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But I have fell into groſs ſins that hath diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured thee, and cauſed thine enemies to blaſpheme.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So did my ſervant <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14. and others of my Saints.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I but then he did mourn and repent greatly for his ſins, but I cannot do ſo, for I find my heart as hard as an Adamant.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So my people <hi>Iſraels</hi> hearts formerly were as hard as a <hi>Rock, Adamant,</hi> and <hi>Flint, Jer.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but I have been long (yea ever) troubled with this hardneſs of heart.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Though thou haſt, yet I will take the ſtony
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:36818:44"/>heart out of thy fleſh, and I will give thee a heart of fleſh, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But I cannot repent me of the hardneſs of my heart.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>What though, yet I am exalted to give repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto thee, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but I do not find that I am ſenſible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of my ſin; for if I were I ſhould mourn, and be aſhamed for all the wickedneſs which I have committed againſt thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>When thou doeſt ſee me whom thou haſt pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and when thou ſeeſt that I am pacified towards thee; then thou ſhalt mourn, loath thy ſelf, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:36818:45"/>be aſhamed, for all thy ſins and abominations which thou haſt committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9. and 16.63.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord I am a very great ſinner, and I would fain ſee the nature and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my ſins, that I might tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent me of them, and be humbled for them.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>If thou ſee all thy ſins with their nature, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and aggravations, thou couldſt never look upon them, but with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas.</hi> And it is not ſo much the ſight of ſin as the ſight of my <hi>Love, Grace, Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> that will lead
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:36818:45"/>thee to repentance, and humble thee for thy ſins, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.42.47. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.3, 4, 5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh Lord I know I am as wicked a ſinner, and as ungodly a wretch as ever lived: but though I know this, yet methinks I am not brok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with the ſence thereof, I cannot weep nor ſhed tears for my ſins, Oh no! I go many times to prayer and to hear Sermons, and there is no more working, nor relenting upon my ſoul, then if I were a dead ſtock, or ſtone.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh my dear ſoul, do not thou belie thy ſelf, for I have heard many a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:36818:46"/>ſigh comming from thy heart, and I have ſeen many a teare drop from thine Eyes: and I will yet pour out more of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of mourning upon thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But what if thou didſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> find theſe things in thy ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet I have offered up ſtrong cries and teares unto my Father for thee, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.17. <hi>Zack.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh Lord that I had but faith to believe that I for my ſelfe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Have faith in me, and be not faithleſs but believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.22. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.27.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord I find ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="85" facs="tcp:36818:46"/>much</hi> Atheiſm <hi>and</hi> unbelief <hi>in my heart, that I have often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times questionings in my ſelfe concerning God, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, and word of God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Theſe are the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and ſuggeſtions of Satan, and my own Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were, and are troubled with them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.25.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh Lord I am troubled with a thouſand temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet fear not (my lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dear Child) for thou haſt divers tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet it is that which my beſt Saints have had, and I will not ſuffer thee to be tempted above what
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:36818:47"/>thou art able, but I will ſuccour thee in thy temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and I will make a way that thou ſhalt eſcape, and be delivered out of temptations, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</p>
                        <p>Chriſtian. <hi>But I think n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Saint hath ſuch temptations a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> mine, for ſometimes, I am temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to kill my ſelfe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to kill others; in ſo much that I cannot look upon any wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, waters, or the like, but I am ready to do my ſelf away there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Satan tempted me to caſt my ſelfe off the Pinacle of the Temple, and he alſo tempted many of my dear Children, to deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:36818:47"/>but do not thou harken to the <hi>Accuſer</hi> (for he doth accuſe thee to me and me to thee) but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay unto him, <hi>Satan</hi> it is written, my Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath over-come thee, and I hope through his blood, and through his might and ſpirit to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thee likewiſe: ſay alſo my God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me not to kill another, nor to do <hi>hurt or violence to my ſelfe:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore get thee behind me thou <hi>Lier, Murtherer,</hi> and <hi>Enemy,</hi> for I will put my truſt in Chriſt though he kill me, and I will endeavour to live to ſerve him, though he
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:36818:48"/>ſhould afterwards damn me <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Job.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.13. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.28. <hi>Job.</hi> 13.15.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Though I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> ſometimes reſolve againſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptations, and labour to reſiſt them: yet I find my temptations are renewed; and I am not able to withſtand them, for they come in as a flood upon me.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I that ſay unto the proud waves, hitherto ſhalt thou come, but no further<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I will by my ſpirit put the Enemy (Satan) to flight when he comes in like a flood againſt thee, <hi>Job.</hi> 38.11. See <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.19. Marg.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord I find
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:36818:48"/>am not only troubled with fear and ſad temptations: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with ſtrong and powerful corruptions.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I will ſubdue all thy iniquities and thy ſins ſhall not have dominion over thee, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh but this doth much trouble me, that I do not find any love in my heart to thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>What though thou doſt not, yet I will circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thy heart and thou ſhalt love me: and when thou apprehendeſt <hi>my</hi> love to thee, thou wilt love me again, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 40.19.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:36818:49"/>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I have ſinned</hi> (Lord) <hi>againſt thy mercies and abaſed thy love, yea love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> my ſins more then thee, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot think that eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> thou wilt look upon me with a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny love or delight.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So did my ſervant <hi>David,</hi> and my people <hi>Iſrael</hi> do, yet as I loved them, ſo will I love the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> freely; and betroth the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to me in loving kindneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and mercy, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 12.8 9. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.5, and 14.4. and 2.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> have not only ſin'd againſt thy mercies but againſt thy correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and chaſtiſements alſo</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:36818:49"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>So did my people <hi>Iſrael</hi> formerly do, for when I ſmote them, they went on forwardly in the way of their evil hearts, but I led them, and reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed comforts to them, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.17.18</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I but my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is worſe then all that, for I have been long under the means of grace, and yet I am altogether fruitleſs; and like the barren Fig-tree.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou troubled ſoul, in me is thy fruit found, and I will purge thee, and thou ſhalt bring forth fruit abundantly, for they that are planted in my houſe ſhall flouriſh and be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:36818:50"/>fat, and like a green Olive Tree, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.12, 13, 14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I Lord, its true if I were a branch in thee, and a true member of thy houſe then I could believe theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of thine; alas! I am neither of both, but ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thee and thy people.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>C.</speaker>
                        <p>Do not ſay that thou art none of mine, (for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> have bought thee with my blood) and do not ſpeak that thou art ſeparated from my people, for I will give thee in mine houſe and within my walls, a place, and a name of Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and Daughters, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.3.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="93" facs="tcp:36818:50"/>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sure if I were not an</hi> out-caſt <hi>and a</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, <hi>I ſhould not be thus (as I am) in a wilderneſs condition.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Iſrael</hi> was counted an <hi>out-caſt,</hi> and ſhe cried out, yet I was then a God to her, and ſhe a people to me, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.16.17.22.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh if I were but one of thine, I ſhould then count my ſelf the happieſt in all the world.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Fear not my Spouſe, for I am thy Husband, and thy Father.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If I were one of thy Children thou wouldſt not hide thy ſelfe from me as thou doſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:36818:51"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I have hid my ſelfe and my face from ſome of my Prophers and people of old, and yet it was in love to them, and ſo it is to thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.14. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.17. and 64.7.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But thou hast hid thy ſelf from me, and thou ſeemeſt alſo to be angry with me, Eſa.</hi> 54.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.9.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Fury is not with me (towards thee) and though I be angry, yet my anger is but for a moment, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 27.4. and 54.8.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yet Lord thou haſt been angry with me a long time, for thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten me.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:36818:51"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Zion did ſay ſo, the Lord hath forſaken me, and my Lord hath forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me: yet I had not forgot her; for ſhe was graven upon the palmes of my hands. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.14.15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.5.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord if thou had'ſt not forgotten me, thou would'ſt never have left me in ſuch a wilderneſs and barren condition as I am in.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I have allured thee into the wilderneſs, that I might ſpeak comfortably unto thee, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.14.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years in trouble, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and wanting peace in my ſoule, which could not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36818:52"/>poſſibly have been, if I had truly believed in thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>But now will I ſpeak peace unto thee, and I will guide thee into the way of peace. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.79.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord wilt thou ſpeak peace unto me and guide me into the way of peace?</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>i. e.</hi> The Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Lips that Preach't peace.</note>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I will create the fruit of the lips <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> and my ſpirit ſhall be in thee, and his fruit ſhall be peace to thy ſoul, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57, 19. and 55.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord thy word ſaith, there is no peace to the wicked.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:36818:52"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>No not to a man that will perſiſt in his wicked way, and doth not nor will not believe in me, but thou art one of thoſe that I bore the chaſtize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy peace, and one of the children of peace, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.5. and 54.13.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord how can I have peace, ſeeing a man cannot have peace before (and without) he does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou ſhalt have faith and peace, and I will give peace through belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.16.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> I muſt know that I am one of thine.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:36818:53"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord thy God, and that thou art one of my people, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.30.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Oh how ſhall I know that.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>My ſpirit ſhall bear witneſs with thy ſpirit that thou art my Child, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But how ſhall I know that it is thy ſpirit that beareth this witneſs, and that it is not the ſpirit of deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou maieſt know that by its power in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thy heart which no other ſpirit can work alike: as alſo by the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36818:53"/>and fruits thereof. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. and 7.22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord what elſe ſhall I believe, beſides being one of thine?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Doſt thou believe that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes Lord, I do believe that thou art Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Son of God, and the Saviour of the world,</hi> Act. 8.37. Joh. 6.69. and 11.27.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>But doſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that I am thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there is no other way to be ſaved but only by thee,</hi> Act. 4.12.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:36818:54"/>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>But doſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that thou ſhalt be ſaved by me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, help my unbelief,</hi> Mar. 9.24.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>To thee it is given to believe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>now Lord I doe believe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>What doſt thou now believe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I believe that thou loved'ſt me and did'ſt give thy ſelf for me, and that thou art my Lord, and my God, and that I am juſtified and ſhall be ſaved by grace,</hi> Gal. 2.20. Joh. 20.28. Act. 15.11.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>How cam'ſt thou to believe this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:36818:54"/>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord it is by thy gift and work that I do believe it,</hi> Eph. 2.8. Heb. 12.2.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Well; now thou doſt believe what wilt thou do?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> Act. 9.6.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>If thou love me, keep my words, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>What are thoſe words of thine?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for they are able to make thee perfect and wiſe unto ſalvation, and to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thee for every good work, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.17.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="102" facs="tcp:36818:55"/>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord how ſhall I underſtand thy word?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>C.</speaker>
                        <p>I will make known my words unto thee, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But Lord is there no danger of my depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and falling away from thee now I do believe?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>No, the Mountains ſhall depart, and the Hills be removed, but my lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thee, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lord I will keep thy precepts with my whole heart,</hi> Phil. 1.19.69.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                        <p>I have redeemed thee that thou ſhould'ſt ſerve me without fear, in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36818:55"/>Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, all the days of thy life: <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.69.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chriſtian,</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Come ye Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and I will declare what my Lord have done for my ſoul.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>My SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L ſhall make her boaſts of the LORD, the humble ſhall hear this and be glad, and magnifie the LORD with me, and let us Exalt his Name together,</hi> Pſal. 34.11.2, 3.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36818:56"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36818:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Threefold State</hi> OF A CHRISTIAN DISCOVERED.</p>
                  <p>viz.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>By Nature.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>By Grace.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>And in Glory.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>With the Character of a Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>A Miſcellany of Divine Contemplations, Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, and Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to a holy Life and Converſation.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>V. P.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thy Threefold State here</l>
                     <l>Thou may'st ſee,</l>
                     <l>What thou haſt been, art,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall be.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed for <hi>N. C.</hi> 1677.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36818:57"/>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:36818:57"/>
                  <head>The Threefold State of a Chriſtian Diſcover'd.</head>
                  <p>1.</p>
                  <p>BY <hi>Nature</hi> I was born of the fleſh, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am born of the Spirit. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall have all Spiritual priviledges, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12.</p>
                  <p>2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was all fleſh. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. &amp; 8.21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am fleſh and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.20.23.25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44.50.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:36818:58"/>3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I walked after the fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I walk in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Gal,</hi> 5.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſpirit. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</p>
                  <p>4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I did mind who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the things of the fleſh <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I do mind chiefly the things of the ſpirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory</hi> I ſhall mind only things ſpiritual.</p>
                  <p>5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was dead in ſin, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:36818:58"/>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am quickened from ſin, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be quite freed from ſin.</p>
                  <p>6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I did lie in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I do live in all pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall enjoy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect purity, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4.</p>
                  <p>7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was under the Law of ſin and death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am made free by the Law of the Spirit of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall triumph over ſin and death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56, 57.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:36818:59"/>8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I did hate God, and his Law, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.21. and 18.15. and 2.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I do love God and his Law, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1. and 11.19.22. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.59.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall for ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in God, and do his Law.</p>
                  <p>9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I deſpiſed all Inſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I deſire all Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 86.11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall attain clear apprehenſion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:36818:59"/>10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the vileſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.49.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I kept company with the beſt Chriſtians <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall know all Saints and live with them, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. - 53 and 15.28. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                  <p>11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I perſecuted Godlineſs, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.14, 15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I profeſs it in power. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall have the price, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:36818:60"/>12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature.</hi> I was one of the world <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.18, 19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am choſen out of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.49. and 25.3.33.</p>
                  <p>13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was in darkneſs 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I walk in the Light <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.12. 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 5.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall dwell with the Light, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16</p>
                  <p>14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was naked and bloody, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:36818:60"/>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am array'd with the robe of Innocency, <hi>Rev,</hi> 29.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be cloathed with Immortallity, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3.</p>
                  <p>15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was a ſtranger, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am Gods freind, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 41.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.10</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite for ever, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.4. and 8.25.</p>
                  <p>16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was an Enemy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am Reconciled, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:36818:61"/>17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am juſtified <hi>Act.</hi> 13.39. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall judg, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28.</p>
                  <p>18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I departed from God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I draw near t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall abide with God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.34.</p>
                  <p>19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was Satha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſlave, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Free-man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.31. 1 <hi>Tet.</hi> 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be a Citiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:36818:61"/>of Zion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.19.</p>
                  <p>20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was free from righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am free through righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall raign in righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.21.</p>
                  <p>21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I lived in fear, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I live by faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I attain the end of my faith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9.</p>
                  <p>22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was without
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:36818:62"/>hope, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I rejoyce in hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall need no hope, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13.</p>
                  <p>23.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was without all the promiſes, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am under all the promiſes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall partake of all things promiſed.</p>
                  <p>24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was the child of the Devil and of Hell, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am a child of God, and a ſtranger in
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:36818:62"/>the world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26.29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be an heir of God and of heaven, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7.</p>
                  <p>25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was in conſtant danger, <hi>Mat</hi> 5.22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am in continual ſafety, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28.29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be in an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable ſanctuary, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17.</p>
                  <p>26.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I ſought to go to Heaven by my own righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I ſeek to go to Heaven without my own
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36818:63"/>righteouſneſs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven abſolutely righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Jud.</hi> 8.14.</p>
                  <p>27.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I ſought my ſelf only, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I ſeek Gods glory chiefly, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall give it to him wholly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.12, 13.</p>
                  <p>28.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was loſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am found, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be at home, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:36818:63"/>29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature</hi> I knew nothing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I know in part, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall know even as I am known. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>30.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> My ſervices were abominable, <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> My ſervices are acceptable, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> My ſervices ſhall be rewarded, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.4. and 10.41.</p>
                  <p>31.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was like a beaſt <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.22. and 45.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am like a Prince, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be like an
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:36818:64"/>Angel, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.36.</p>
                  <p>32.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> My body was the Temple of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> My body is the Temple of the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> My body ſhall be raiſed ſpiritual, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44.</p>
                  <p>33.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I did glory in my ſhame, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am aſhamed of my ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be without ſin and ſhame, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28.</p>
                  <p>34.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature,</hi> I was like the dirt and mire, moſt fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:36818:64"/>
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.20. and 10.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I am like the Moon in beauty, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall be like the Sun in Glory, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.43.</p>
                  <p>35.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Nature</hi> I ſate in the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.79.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Grace,</hi> I do ſit virtually in the Kingdom of Life, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Glory,</hi> I ſhall ſit on his Throne Eternally, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.40. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:36818:65"/>
                  <head>The Character of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, with ſome Divine Contemplations, Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Directions to a Holy Life.</head>
                  <p>1.</p>
                  <p>A True Chriſtian is one that hath had clear convictions of <hi>ſin,</hi> (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally his Maſter ſin &amp; unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief) and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is, the want and worth of him; and of <hi>Judgment,</hi> that is, of puniſhment, as the due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of ſin, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:36818:65"/>2.</p>
                  <p>He is unbottomed and broken off from himſelf, he hath no confidence in himſelf; his Birth, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Parts, Performances, and beſt works, are impure and imperfect in his own ſight, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6.</p>
                  <p>3.</p>
                  <p>He is hardly brought to believe; he hardly believes that he doth believe, and hardly caſts away his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, when he doth once truly believe.</p>
                  <p>4.</p>
                  <p>Upon ſelfe ſuſpition he doth greatly deſire to be ſearched, and doth earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſearch himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.1.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:36818:66"/>and laſt, and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.6.</p>
                  <p>5.</p>
                  <p>He doth reſolve never to go on in any ſin, or to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect any duty.</p>
                  <p>6.</p>
                  <p>He prays to God moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>deareſt</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſin,</hi> and praiſes God moſt when he hath power againſt it.</p>
                  <p>7.</p>
                  <p>He never repents for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſin he hath forſaken, for any good he hath done, or for any affliction he hath ſuffered for Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>8.</p>
                  <p>He hath Love to all Chriſtians, and ſeeks Unity among all, and makes U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36818:66"/>and Godlineſs the ground of his fellowſhip and Communion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9, 10.</p>
                  <p>9.</p>
                  <p>In reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he obſerves what helps on his holineſs, and teacheth ſelf-denial, as well as what increaſeth knowledg.</p>
                  <p>10.</p>
                  <p>He cares not what he hath, whether he goes, nor what he ſuffers with Chriſt and for him without ſin.</p>
                  <p>11.</p>
                  <p>His faith helps on his holineſs, and his holineſs helps up his faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:36818:67"/>12.</p>
                  <p>Though he alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to follow Chriſt, through every <hi>condition,</hi> yet he much ſuſpects and fears that he ſhall not be able to hold out.</p>
                  <p>13.</p>
                  <p>He ſeeks and prizes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to ſerve God here, as much as happineſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <p>14.</p>
                  <p>He fears God and ſin, more then men and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17.18.</p>
                  <p>15.</p>
                  <p>He neglects not his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty though he knows there is great danger in doing of it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:36818:67"/>16.</p>
                  <p>He is one that is careful to lay in, and to get true grace in his heart, as well as in his profeſſion; as the wiſe Scribe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. and wiſe Virgin, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</p>
                  <p>17.</p>
                  <p>He can and dare do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the Truth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. eſpecially if he knows it.</p>
                  <p>18.</p>
                  <p>He cleaves to the Lord, and follows after the Lord fully in the worſt times, and when others forſake him, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.24. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.68.</p>
                  <p>19.</p>
                  <p>He reſpects all, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects none of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:36818:68"/>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.23.</p>
                  <p>20.</p>
                  <p>He takes patiently and thankfully, the harſheſt words and the hardeſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.19. <hi>Job.</hi> 1.14. to the end.</p>
                  <p>21.</p>
                  <p>He is much affected with, and afflicted for the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Godly, and the ſins of the wicked; as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Jeremiah, Lot, Paul, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>22.</p>
                  <p>He is one that when he is recovered from his former backſliding, remembers his former good condition and prizes it, and praiſes God,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:36818:68"/>and hates his ſin more then he did before, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. and 14.2.3.8.</p>
                  <p>23.</p>
                  <p>He ſeeks and eſteems ſincerity more then any garniſhing gifts &amp; prizes, plain and poor Chriſtians that are honeſt and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, more then they that have parts and wealth if they be leſs ſincere.</p>
                  <p>24.</p>
                  <p>He is one that exerciſeth a good conſcience in all things.</p>
                  <p>25.</p>
                  <p>He is one that fears God and his name, and deſires Grace for Grace ſake, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:36818:69"/>26.</p>
                  <p>He is one that prays at his firſt converſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.11. God hath no ſtill-born Children.</p>
                  <p>27.</p>
                  <p>He beholds Chriſt in the deepeſt affliction, as well as in the moſt ſpiritual or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</p>
                  <p>28.</p>
                  <p>He believes he ſhall ſooner overcome his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Enemies by praying for them, then by praying againſt them.</p>
                  <p>29.</p>
                  <p>He prefers Chriſt before ſelf, and ſuffering before ſinning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:36818:69"/>30.</p>
                  <p>He deſires to live ſo <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> that we may keep Chriſt in heaven <hi>undiſpleaſed;</hi> the ſpirit within him <hi>ungreiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> his conſcience <hi>undefiled, unwounded</hi> and <hi>unſeared,</hi> his profeſſion <hi>unſtained,</hi> his brethren <hi>unoffended,</hi> and poor ſinners <hi>unſtumbled.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>31.</p>
                  <p>His care is to wait on God, to walk with God, to work all his works in and for God, to bring his will to ſubmit to the will of God in all things, to glorifie God, and to gain good to himſelf by all he doth and ſuffereth, to do what good he can to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:36818:70"/>and receive what good he can from other Chriſtians to deny himſelf, and to be found in Chriſts righteouſneſs without his own, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                  <p>32.</p>
                  <p>A true Chriſtian will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be freed from, 1. Doubts of his Eternal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, 2. From the power of corruption, 3. From the fire of the Law in his conſcience, 4. From the fierce Temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, 5. From ſcruples in matters of opinion, 6. From wicked places and perſons, where he can neither do, nor receive good, nor be without danger of Evil,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:36818:70"/>7. From a bad frame of heart, as hardneſs, ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Lukewarmneſs, 8. From the fear of Death.</p>
                  <p>33.</p>
                  <p>A true Chriſtian deſires, 1. To know God in Chriſt, 2. To know himſelf in Chriſt, 3. To know Chriſt in him, 4. To know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as he was without Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Wicked and wretched in reſpect of ſin, unwilling to good, and weak in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9.10, 11. and 8.7. and 5.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:36818:71"/>
                  <head>A Miſcellany of Divine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations, Obſervations and Directions to a Holy Life.</head>
                  <p>1.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtian is to put forth his faith in prayer, and afterwards to follow his prayer with faith.</p>
                  <p>2.</p>
                  <p>Reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture helps <hi>Meditation, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation</hi> Prayer, and Prayer every good work.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:36818:71"/>3.</p>
                  <p>Man may come too late to God when the door is ſhut, but God never comes too late to men, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.6.</p>
                  <p>4.</p>
                  <p>Pray that thy laſt days and laſt works may be beſt, and that when thou comeſt to die, thou maiſt have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to do but to die.</p>
                  <p>5.</p>
                  <p>'Tis very hard to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our own gifts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pride, and the gifts of others (if they excel ours) without envy.</p>
                  <p>6.</p>
                  <p>Do not commend thy friend, nor diſcommend
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:36818:72"/>thy ſoe too much, leaſt thou be judged to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial.</p>
                  <p>7.</p>
                  <p>Oh my Soul! will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great <hi>Love,</hi> great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, great Forbearance, great Intreaty, great Patience, great Promiſes, nor great Wages, prevail with thee to ſerve Chriſt free, better, and more conſtant and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying.</p>
                  <p>8.</p>
                  <p>A deep ſence of ſin, begets deep ſorrow for ſin; and true ſorrow for ſin leads to well-grounded faith; and from hence flows inward Peace, Joy, and Holineſs,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:36818:72"/>9.</p>
                  <p>A Paſſionate and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſpirit is like a little Rill of water, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhower of rain changeth the colour of it, and makes it muddy.</p>
                  <p>10.</p>
                  <p>The fear of death is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted in the common Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all men, but faith works it out of Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>11.</p>
                  <p>Nothing will be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble where the love of God is apprehended, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing grievous where love to Chriſt is excerciſed.</p>
                  <p>12.</p>
                  <p>Careleſs hearing makes carnal hearts, and carnal
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:36818:73"/>hearts makes curſed lives.</p>
                  <p>13.</p>
                  <p>Oh my Soul! look for death hourly, long for it greatly, prepare for it care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, meet and welcome it joyfully for it is Chriſts ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to direct his ſpouſe (the Soul) to him, and thy friend that comes to ſet thee at liberty from thy ſins; It will diſcharge thee from thy priſon, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt thee from thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and bring thee at once to enjoy all thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
                  <p>14.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtians, though diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grecing in opinion, ſhould agree in affection; and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:36818:73"/>though differing in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, yet ſhould agree in charity.</p>
                  <p>15.</p>
                  <p>He that cannot pitty the ſinner and hate ſin, doth not reprove out of love to Chriſt, nor from a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>16.</p>
                  <p>God makes Chriſtians <hi>feel</hi> him, (or his hand) that he may <hi>hear</hi> them; ſtrokes makes crys, and whippings mournful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to him.</p>
                  <p>17.</p>
                  <p>My Soul! bear up with Chriſt, bear off from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and the world, bear down thy corruptions,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:36818:74"/>and bear forth thy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
                  <p>18.</p>
                  <p>Clear knowledge of Chriſt in the <hi>underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> begets fervent love in the <hi>heart;</hi> and both godlineſs in the life.</p>
                  <p>19.</p>
                  <p>He that would live for himſelfe (only or cheifly) in the world, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to live a day in it.</p>
                  <p>20.</p>
                  <p>I would be glad to be out of the world when I have no ſervice to do for God in it.</p>
                  <p>21.</p>
                  <p>God hath ſet the tongue between the brains and
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:36818:74"/>heart, that it may adviſe with both, and guarded it with Teeth to keep it in, and yet how unruly it is.</p>
                  <p>22.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtians ſecurity, and ſafety is, in doing his duty; and he ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Study his duty more then his ſafety; for if he will take care to pleaſe God, God will take care to preſerve him.</p>
                  <p>23.</p>
                  <p>The love of the Maſter, the ſweetneſs of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the greatneſs of the reward, are ſufficient encouragements to ſerve Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:36818:75"/>24.</p>
                  <p>The heavieſt afflictions on earth are but light in compariſon of Chriſts ſufferings, ſins deſert, or the punniſhment of the wicked in Hell.</p>
                  <p>25.</p>
                  <p>Lay in, lay up, lay out for Chriſt, and remember that you will ſhortly reach immortallity, but never Eternity.</p>
                  <p>26.</p>
                  <p>Oh Chriſtian, why ſhould not he pleaſe thee, who art but finite, that pleaſes <hi>God</hi> who is infinite, even Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>27.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtian ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:36818:75"/>to dye that he may be <hi>fully</hi> freed from ſin, and have a <hi>full</hi> fruition of Chriſt that he may be above all fears and doubts, and may be able to ſerve the Lord inceſſantly and unwearied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p>28.</p>
                  <p>A true Chriſtian when he goes from hence, changes neither his work nor company; but his place and condition only.</p>
                  <p>29.</p>
                  <p>Be ſtill imployed in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and you ſhall not be much tempted, or troubled with evil, for the Devil hath great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, both againſt thoſe
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:36818:76"/>that are idle or ill-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. <hi>David</hi> was found guilty of the firſt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2. and <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> in the laſt, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 10.31.</p>
                  <p>30.</p>
                  <p>Sence of <hi>Miſery</hi> muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede ſence of <hi>Mercy,</hi> and the more we feel and fear <hi>Miſery,</hi> the more we deſire, ſeek for, and prize <hi>Mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>31.</p>
                  <p>It is the leaſt of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be afflicted by men, for they can afflict but the outward man only; and of all E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emies man is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>my; But <hi>God,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, yea <hi>Satan,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> do afflict the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> is more intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:36818:76"/>32.</p>
                  <p>That Chriſtian is moſt in prayer that hath moſt ſence of his own wants, and is moſt comfortable ordinarily, that is moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and the ſame word in the <hi>Greek</hi> ſignifies to <hi>want</hi> and to <hi>pray;</hi> and the ſame word in Hebrew, to <hi>repent,</hi> and to <hi>comfort.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>33.</p>
                  <p>Be more thoughtful and careful how to uſe what you have to Gods glory, then to gain more.</p>
                  <p>34.</p>
                  <p>Take heed of being <hi>humbled</hi> and yet <hi>unhumbled,</hi> that is, of being brought outwardly <hi>Low,</hi> and yet
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:36818:77"/>the heart continue ſtill high.</p>
                  <p>35.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes <hi>Ejaculations,</hi> or ſhort and ſuddain <hi>pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> and <hi>breathings</hi> out of deſires to God, may be more acceptable to him, and more prevailing with him then long prayers.</p>
                  <p>36.</p>
                  <p>Never reckon what thou haſt of outward &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, unleſs it be to praiſe God for them, or to ſerve, God better with them.</p>
                  <p>37.</p>
                  <p>It is the property of a true Chriſtian to juſtifie God, and to judg himſelf
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:36818:77"/>under the greateſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>38.</p>
                  <p>Learn to know ſin, to diſallow of it, to diſpiſe it, to overcome it inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and to put it from thee: to fear its return, and to be more eſtranged toward it, more watchful to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Temptations, and wiſe to ſhun occaſions that lead to it.</p>
                  <p>39.</p>
                  <p>To dye ſhould be no more to a Chriſtian then to breath, or to paſs over a great River on a ſure Bridge, or in a ſafe Boat, or to return from a field where a man hath been
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:36818:78"/>working, to his own houſe to take his reſt.</p>
                  <p>40.</p>
                  <p>Make haſt to do thy <hi>work</hi> (Chriſtian) and God will make haſt to give thee thy <hi>wages.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>41.</p>
                  <p>The hardeſt dutys in Chriſtianity are, to deny ſelf, and to deſtroy ſin.</p>
                  <p>42.</p>
                  <p>A heart unconverted, is contented with nothing but what is helping it on to Hell, and it hath never enough of that (to wit ſin); and a heart conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is never ſatisfied but with what helps it toward
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:36818:78"/>
                     <hi>heaven,</hi> and yet thinks he hath never enough there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; to wit Chriſt and Grace.</p>
                  <p>43.</p>
                  <p>To take pains about un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary and unprofitable things, is laboriouſly to miſpend time.</p>
                  <p>44.</p>
                  <p>Get Chriſt (O Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) to bind thy conſcience to the <hi>peace,</hi> and thy affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and fleſh to the <hi>good behaviour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>45.</p>
                  <p>Be not ambitious of love, and greatneſs, and thou ſhalt not be ſo ſoon an object of Envy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:36818:79"/>46.</p>
                  <p>He that converts a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, covers a world (or multitude) of ſins, and gains more then a world, to wit, a Soul, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.30.</p>
                  <p>47.</p>
                  <p>Take heed of covering any mans good with his evil, but let the one plead for him, as well as the other againſt him.</p>
                  <p>48.</p>
                  <p>One of the chiefeſt works of the ſoul, is ſelfe examination, and yet a Chriſtian will find himſelf moſt backward thereto, and ſooneſt weary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:36818:79"/>49.</p>
                  <p>Seaſonable and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected mercys are very ſweet and acceptable.</p>
                  <p>50.</p>
                  <p>The more a ſoul is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in <hi>ſpiritual medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the leſs with <hi>carnal Temptation;</hi> and the more frequent and powerful in private prayer, the more free from, and the more potent againſt Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>51.</p>
                  <p>Sin was condemned by Chriſt to ſave the ſinner, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. Oh! then let not the ſinner ſeek to ſave the ſin, to wound Chriſt again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:36818:80"/>52.</p>
                  <p>Quick <hi>onſets</hi> and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to reform, are far better then many <hi>purpoſes</hi> and <hi>Reſolutions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>53.</p>
                  <p>Small ſins yielded to make way for greater, and one ſin for another.</p>
                  <p>54.</p>
                  <p>Be ſure to praiſe God when you receive power againſt ſin and Temptation; and you ſhall be ſure to find God ready to give you power another time when you want it.</p>
                  <p>55.</p>
                  <p>When and where wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is moſt, then and there the godly ſhould
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:36818:80"/>ſtrive to be moſt godly. It is a ſign of ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be good in bad times and in bad places and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong bad perſons, as <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, Lot,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> were.</p>
                  <p>56.</p>
                  <p>At the day of death (but eſpecially at the day of Judgment) a Chriſtian will wiſh he had ſinned leſs, ſerved God, and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him more.</p>
                  <p>57.</p>
                  <p>If Chriſtians were not ſometimes afflicted, they would forget both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others; for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction works humiliation in men themſelves, and compaſſion toward others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:36818:81"/>58.</p>
                  <p>It is a hard thing for a profane man to attain the <hi>Shaddow</hi> of Religion; or for a careleſs (though true) Chriſtian to attain the <hi>ſubſtance.</hi> And it is hard for a true Chriſtian that hath the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> to keep up the <hi>ſence</hi> and <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> either of the <hi>excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of Jeſus, or the <hi>evil</hi> of ſin, always in his heart.</p>
                  <p>59.</p>
                  <p>Oh! what time do Chriſtians miſpend; what duties do they neglect, what mercies do they ſlight, what corruptions do they embrace, what Temptations do they lie
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:36818:81"/>under; what corrections do they undervalue. Oh! what heart qualms, and fleſhly weakneſſes cry out upon us to make ready? and yet how unready, how unripe, how unwilling, how unmindful, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughtful are we of our latter end? and this is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are unaſſured of Chriſt, unweaned from the world, unweary of ſin, unbroken from ſelf, and unapprehenſive of the glory to be revealed and enjoyed hereafter.</p>
                  <p>60.</p>
                  <p>Fear thy friends more then thy foes, thy ſins more then thy ſufferings,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:36818:82"/>and liberty more then bondage.</p>
                  <p>61.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtians ſhould not give offence <hi>careleſly,</hi> nor take offence <hi>cauſleſly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>62.</p>
                  <p>Bad times well Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, are far better then good times not redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or miſpent.</p>
                  <p>63.</p>
                  <p>It is and ſhall be the care of a Chriſtian, not to ſuffer for ſin, nor to ſin in ſuffering.</p>
                  <p>64.</p>
                  <p>There is no real bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, but what is either from ſin, or for ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:36818:82"/>65.</p>
                  <p>Affections, parts, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe from the world, or from Chriſtians are very dangerous, and not to be truſted in.</p>
                  <p>66.</p>
                  <p>I never truſted Chriſt but I found him faithful; nor my own heart, but I found it falſe.</p>
                  <p>67.</p>
                  <p>Shut thy eyes from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding thy ears from hearing and thy heart from entertaining ſin.</p>
                  <p>68.</p>
                  <p>Take heed of reproving or upbraiding another in paſſion, or to provoke them thereto; for 'tis
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:36818:83"/>better be ſilent, then ſin in ſpeaking; 'tis better to keep thy light under a buſhel, then to put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hand of him that will blow it out, or tread it under his feet.</p>
                  <p>69.</p>
                  <p>Self-loathing, deſtroys ſelf-love, and the more we loath our ſelves, the better we love others.</p>
                  <p>70.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtians ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy the patience of God toward their enemies, for it is nothing in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what grace he ſhows to them.</p>
                  <p>71.</p>
                  <p>Of all men a Chriſtian
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:36818:83"/>may be freer to loſe or to part with any thing then another man, for he loſes nothing but what is hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him (to wit his ſins) or what he ſhall regain and recover of a better ſort, and in a more abundant degree. As if he loſe a ſmall <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Eſtate,</hi> he hath in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion an <hi>Eternal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> If he lays down a body that is <hi>full of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> he ſhall have another free from corruption; and therefore he may ſay, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the Heathen could, <hi>what I keep, I loſe, and what I give or lay out, I ſave.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:36818:84"/>72.</p>
                  <p>Sins beſt is before, but its worſt is behind; and the ſting and Tayl of it is longer then it ſelf; where ſin is not killed, it will kill.</p>
                  <p>73.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtians converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould keep from the ſhew of ſin, and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience from the guilt of it.</p>
                  <p>74.</p>
                  <p>The power and ſtrength of corruption is but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome known, to wit, when <hi>Temptations, Opportunities,</hi> and <hi>Occaſions</hi> of Tryal come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:36818:84"/>75.</p>
                  <p>The beſt way to keep from Sin, is to ſet God in his power, Purity, and Glory ſtill before our eyes; to fear our ſelves, to keep near Chriſt, to faſt and pray privately; to engage other Chriſtians for our help; to cheriſh the holy ſpirit, to keep up con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice of holineſs; to provide contrary means againſt it, to reſolve ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to withſtand it, to eye Gods promiſes, commands and threatnings; to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the firſt occaſions of ſin; to reaſon it off at a diſtance, to believe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way when it comes near;
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:36818:85"/>to avoid all occaſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to keep on ſtill the Armour of God.</p>
                  <p>76.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtians are often apt to be moſt weary of that condition that doth them moſt good; like <hi>Peter,</hi> not underſtanding what Chriſt did in waſhing his feet, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.1.9.</p>
                  <p>77.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtians in and under afflictions, ſhould be grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy; and through their afflictions ſhould be going on toward happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; affliction is part of the way of ſanctification leading to ſalvation, and it is like an up-hil, leading
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:36818:85"/>to an houſe that is on the top of an hill, for ſo is heaven; and the greateſt hardſhip is neareſt the end of the journey.</p>
                  <p>78.</p>
                  <p>They have but a ſlight profeſſion whoſe profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth not lead them out of ſin and through ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, &amp; he that is worſe under affliction, as <hi>Ahar,</hi> may well fuſpect his own ſincerity.</p>
                  <p>79.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt will ſoon be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of thoſe Chriſtians <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,</hi> that are ſenſible of their own <hi>ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>80.</p>
                  <p>It ought to be a great
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:36818:86"/>part of a Chriſtians trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he can be no time what he ſhould be, that is, <hi>ſinleſs</hi> and <hi>ſervicable;</hi> that he is not at all times, what he is ſometimes, that is, <hi>ſlighting ſin, Judging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Loving Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſing</hi> the world greatly.</p>
                  <p>81.</p>
                  <p>It is ſtrange, and a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad ſign, to ſee Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, look more upon the ſins of the wicked; to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen them for <hi>miſery,</hi> then to mind ſelf-humiliation and holineſs, to ripen and fit themſelves for <hi>mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>82.</p>
                  <p>He loves not a reprover, not values his reproof, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:36818:86"/>profits thereby; but is more his <hi>ſins</hi> then his <hi>ſouls</hi> Friend.</p>
                  <p>83.</p>
                  <p>'Tis a ſign of a hard heart to deſire the <hi>Eternal</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the wicked, for obtaining of their own <hi>Temporal,</hi> and <hi>Corporal</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, ſafety, or honour; as if one ſhould deſire to have another caſt into the fire and be burnt, that himſelf may be warmed thereby.</p>
                  <p>84.</p>
                  <p>In the midſt of earthly buſineſſes the ſoul ſhould redeem ſome ſpecial time for <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>private</hi> duties.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:36818:87"/>85.</p>
                  <p>It is the will of Chriſt that Chriſtians ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce more in what Chriſt hath done for them, then in what they have done or can do for him.</p>
                  <p>86.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt kept the Law <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally,</hi> Chriſtians kept it <hi>evangellically;</hi> He kept it <hi>perfectly,</hi> they kept it with <hi>full purpoſe</hi> and <hi>endeavour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>87.</p>
                  <p>Ask thy ſoul (O Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian) whether he be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own Terms, and for his own ſake, and to accept of pardon and life through him freely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:36818:87"/>looking at all upon thy own righteouſneſs. Art thou contented that Chriſt ſhould be honoured in and by thee, and that thou ſhouldſt be deſpiſed, and diſhonoured for his ſake?</p>
                  <p>88.</p>
                  <p>God doth never out-ſpeak, or out-promiſe his <hi>Power, Truth</hi> and <hi>Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>89.</p>
                  <p>He is a ſtrong Chriſtian that ſeeks Gods Glory more then his own ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but he is no Chriſtian that ſeeks neither.</p>
                  <p>90.</p>
                  <p>It is a great eaſe to, and an unburtherning of the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:36818:88"/>to confeſs ſin, <hi>ſenſibly, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, brokenly,</hi> and with hatred to it.</p>
                  <p>91.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt and ſin are moſt magnified in the eyes of believers in their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but in a very different manner, and to a different end: For Chriſt appears as the <hi>greateſt good,</hi> and ſin as the <hi>greateſt evil;</hi> and then Chriſt will be moſt <hi>deſired,</hi> and ſin moſt <hi>deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>92.</p>
                  <p>It is the duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to ſuſpect and ſearch himſelf, when he doth not know evil by himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:36818:88"/>93.</p>
                  <p>Account the leaſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual thing better then the greateſt and beſt of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and temporal things.</p>
                  <p>94.</p>
                  <p>Keeking from ſin is <hi>Soul-preſervative Phyſick;</hi> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for ſin is <hi>Soul-Reſtorative Phyſick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>95.</p>
                  <p>Strive greatly to have and excerciſe a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience toward God and men; to commit thy Soul, Life, and condition to the Lord; and then expect the worſt of men, and the ſteb of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>96.</p>
                  <p>Thou muſt die once
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:36818:89"/>whether thou <hi>ſuffer or no,</hi> and thou canſt but die once if thou <hi>ſuffer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>97.</p>
                  <p>The ſins of Chriſtians are new ſufferings to Chriſt; and the ſufferings of Chriſtians are wounds of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9.</p>
                  <p>98.</p>
                  <p>Labour to act thoſe Graces chiefly that are moſt contrary to your <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>99.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtian may know the weight of <hi>ſin,</hi> by the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of Chriſt; for if that ſtrong Bar of Steel did bend under the weight
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:36818:89"/>of our ſins; what ſhall poor weak man do, who is but a reed or ruſh.</p>
                  <p>100.</p>
                  <p>Sathan <hi>accuſes</hi> God to men, and men to God; but Chriſt <hi>excuſes</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers all his accuſations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people.</p>
                  <p>101.</p>
                  <p>He that will not take <hi>example</hi> from others, ſhall make an <hi>example</hi> himſelf.</p>
                  <p>102.</p>
                  <p>O Lord as a ſign that I ſhall be able to <hi>die</hi> for thee! let me find my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions <hi>dying</hi> in me, by power from thee.</p>
                  <p>103.</p>
                  <p>He that <hi>loves not</hi> Chriſt
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:36818:90"/>more then his life, is like to loſe Chriſt, and his life; but he that <hi>loves</hi> Chriſt more than his life, will be ſure to ſave and keep both, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.49. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26.</p>
                  <p>104.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtians ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>reſtraints</hi> from ſin, <hi>great mercys</hi> to them, but <hi>Recoveries</hi> out of ſin, with ſpiritual advantage, <hi>greater.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>105.</p>
                  <p>Sin hath no <hi>Mother</hi> but a mans heart, nor <hi>Father</hi> but Satan.</p>
                  <p>106.</p>
                  <p>Satan draws the Soul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, either by <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Policy</hi> by <hi>Force</hi> or by <hi>Fraud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:36818:90"/>107.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtian ſhould deſire to have his heart tyed to the Lord, and to be ſtrong in faith upon Chriſt, in Love to Chriſt, and in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution for him.</p>
                  <p>108.</p>
                  <p>The reaſon why men do not more magnifie <hi>Gods grace,</hi> is becauſe they do not behold their own <hi>vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and the reaſon why men do not ſee their own <hi>vileneſs</hi> more, is becauſe they do not apprehend <hi>Gods goodneſs</hi> more clearly and fully.</p>
                  <p>109.</p>
                  <p>When a Chriſtian comes to be as weary of his <hi>ſins</hi> as
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:36818:91"/>of his <hi>afflictions,</hi> God will certainly put an end to them.</p>
                  <p>110.</p>
                  <p>There will be a reviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>old ſins,</hi> if there be not <hi>effectual repentance</hi> for them, and a care by <hi>faith</hi> through all <hi>duties</hi> and <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> to get new ſtrength againſt them, and a conſtant watch kept over them.</p>
                  <p>111.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtian comes not to know the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of his <hi>grace,</hi> till the ſpirit ceaſes to work in and by it; nor the <hi>power</hi> of his <hi>corruption</hi> till Satan works therein by his Temptations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="175" facs="tcp:36818:91"/>112.</p>
                  <p>It ſhould trouble a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian much to have ſuch <hi>Graces</hi> as he receives from God, beget ſo little good in him.</p>
                  <p>113.</p>
                  <p>The Lord would ſoon turn from his <hi>wrath,</hi> if men were turned from their <hi>wickedneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>114.</p>
                  <p>He commands <hi>moſt</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> that commands in love, humility, and ſelf-denyal.</p>
                  <p>115.</p>
                  <p>The world is a <hi>great no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> deluding the <hi>bad,</hi> and diſturbing and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the <hi>good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="176" facs="tcp:36818:92"/>116.</p>
                  <p>The Holy Law of God teaches a man to ſee his own <hi>deformity,</hi> and requires from a man <hi>Conformity</hi> to it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>117.</p>
                  <p>Sathan works more upon men by <hi>ſlight</hi> then by <hi>might;</hi> avoid therefore his <hi>cunning,</hi> and thou wilt avoid his <hi>cruelty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>118.</p>
                  <p>He hath not learned to <hi>rule</hi> well, that hath not learned to <hi>obey</hi> well.</p>
                  <p>119.</p>
                  <p>An even, through-paced, ſelf-fearing, heart-melting Chriſtian is always beſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="177" facs="tcp:36818:92"/>120.</p>
                  <p>Ruſling, opinion-ſour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Church-renting perſons, and profeſſors, have commonly more <hi>ſelf</hi> then <hi>grace,</hi> if any at all.</p>
                  <p>121.</p>
                  <p>The leſs a man <hi>ſtrives</hi> for himſelf, the more will Chriſt <hi>ſtrive</hi> for him.</p>
                  <p>122.</p>
                  <p>Thoughts of our own <hi>death</hi> will much tend to <hi>deaden</hi> ſin.</p>
                  <p>123.</p>
                  <p>Prayer is a good prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative to ſuffering; when Chriſt had prayed, he went out to meet <hi>Judas, Joh.</hi> 18.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="178" facs="tcp:36818:93"/>124.</p>
                  <p>Be never at peace with <hi>ſin, Satan,</hi> or Chriſts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Enemies.</p>
                  <p>125.</p>
                  <p>In two caſes 'tis hard to act Faith. 1. When there is nothing ſenſible or viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſecond and ſupport it. 2. When there is very much of theſe outward things to fill and take the ſenſes withal.</p>
                  <p>126.</p>
                  <p>As Chriſt was ſaved from <hi>death</hi> though he <hi>died, Heb.</hi> 5.7. So are true Chriſtians when they overcome <hi>death</hi> by <hi>their reſurrection</hi> through Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="179" facs="tcp:36818:93"/>127.</p>
                  <p>Learn by <hi>lighter croſſes</hi> to look and prepare for <hi>heavier.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>128.</p>
                  <p>As our <hi>good works and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rformances</hi> ſhould have an operation upon our ſouls and hearts to ſtrengthen <hi>faith,</hi> ſo ſhould our <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> and <hi>ſins</hi> to work <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>129.</p>
                  <p>No power can keep him in <hi>Bond</hi> whom truth and innocency acquits.</p>
                  <p>130.</p>
                  <p>If thou haſt faln into <hi>ſin</hi> through violent tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſeek ſpeedily for <hi>Repentance</hi> for it, <hi>recovery</hi>
                     <pb n="180" facs="tcp:36818:94"/>out of it, and <hi>Reformation</hi> under it. If God hath kept thee from falling, ſtill fear, watch, pray, and live by faith in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>131.</p>
                  <p>Prepare your ſelf for death and pull out its ſting. 1. By bewailing ſins paſt. 2. Turning to God in time to come. 3. Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a new life, none can <hi>dy ill</hi> that hath had a care of <hi>living well;</hi> perſwade your ſelf, if you <hi>live well,</hi> you ſhall <hi>die well;</hi> and if you <hi>die well,</hi> doubt not but you ſhall have Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>132.</p>
                  <p>Wiſh not for a <hi>long</hi> life,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:36818:94"/>ſo much as for a <hi>good</hi> life; he hath lived <hi>long</hi> who hath lived <hi>well;</hi> a <hi>ſhort</hi> life in <hi>grace,</hi> endeth in an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life of <hi>Glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>133.</p>
                  <p>Diſtruſt not Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in any matter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you ſee the means wanting, neither when you have them, let them be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed on more then God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but pray to him for the proſperous uſe of them.</p>
                  <p>134.</p>
                  <p>Love all things for Gods ſake, and God only for his own, and look you make him your friend who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever be your enemy for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this you ſhall do, if as an
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:36818:95"/>obedient Child, you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways live in the eye of your heavenly Father.</p>
                  <p>135.</p>
                  <p>Give no offence to any man juſtly, whether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or without; for wo to them by whom offences come.</p>
                  <p>136.</p>
                  <p>Carry your ſelf unto all, ſo as the <hi>weak</hi> may be <hi>won,</hi> the <hi>ſtrong</hi> may be <hi>comforted,</hi> and the <hi>wicked</hi> be <hi>aſhamed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>137.</p>
                  <p>Delight to do all the good you can to Gods Children, and to receive all the good you can from them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="183" facs="tcp:36818:95"/>138.</p>
                  <p>Think it the greateſt work in the world to die well, which to do, you muſt inure your ſelf to die before hand. 1. By dying to your ſins. 2. Learning the word of affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it actually leave you. 3. In your laſt learning of if, do it willingly, yea joyfully, whenſoever, whereſoever, or howſoever God ſhall call you.</p>
                  <p>139.</p>
                  <p>Greive for nothing ſo much in the world, as for your own ſins, and in them for nothing ſo much as for offending ſo loving a God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="184" facs="tcp:36818:96"/>140.</p>
                  <p>Let your meat, apparel, and recreation be lawful, needful, and moderate.</p>
                  <p>141.</p>
                  <p>Labour alwaies to learn to die, defie the world, deny the Devil, deſpiſe the fleſh, and delight your ſelf in the Lord; be peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for your ſins paſt and preſent, and yet deſpair not; be ſtrong in Faith, and yet preſume not. Deſire with the great Apoſtle to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, with whom even in death, there is life.</p>
                  <p>142.</p>
                  <p>Uſe your life, and keep
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:36818:96"/>it with as much quietneſs as you can, ſo that you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend not God; that eaſe that cometh with his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure turneth at length to an unſpeakable pain, and the gain of the world, with the loſs of his favour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, is extream beggary and wretchedneſs.</p>
                  <p>143.</p>
                  <p>The greateſt honour that man can give to God, is to confeſs his truth tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully in time of trouble and affliction.</p>
                  <p>144.</p>
                  <p>It is but a folly for any one that truly profeſſeth Chriſt crucified, to look for the love of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="186" facs="tcp:36818:97"/>145.</p>
                  <p>Infidelity is the cauſe of all our miſery, which cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to fear man more then God, and to eſteem things preſent, more than things to come.</p>
                  <p>146.</p>
                  <p>Love is that flower which ſhall never fade, but ſhall flouriſh more and more, till it be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in that place, where Faith and Hope ſhall have no office, but ſhall then ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſs that which they have ſo <hi>long</hi> patiently wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for in this world.</p>
                  <p>147.</p>
                  <p>After the Lord hath made a Chriſtian to know
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:36818:97"/>what he is in himſelf, he will doubtleſs ſhew him comfort, and declare to him what he is in Jeſus Chriſt his Son.</p>
                  <p>148.</p>
                  <p>The mind of man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be contented pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to bear the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles either of Soul or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, until it be regenerated and poſſeſſed by Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
                  <p>149.</p>
                  <p>Why ſhould we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans fear death? can death deprive us of Chriſt, who is all our comfort, our joy, and our life.</p>
                  <p>150.</p>
                  <p>Let us tarry with Chriſt
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:36818:98"/>one hour in Tribulation and affliction, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he will keep us for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with him in joys ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
                  <p>151.</p>
                  <p>Patience and Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance under great tryals are the proper <hi>notes</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gods children are known from counterfeits; they that perſevere not, were alwaies but Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</p>
                  <p>152.</p>
                  <p>If Chriſt be our Captain we muſt follow him as good Souldiers; if we keep company with him in afflictions, we ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re of his ſociety in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:36818:98"/>if we forſake not him, he will never forſake us; if we confeſs him, he will confeſs us; if we be aſhamed of him, he will be aſhamed of us. Therefore as he forſook Father, Heaven, and all things to come to us, ſo let us forſake all things to come to him, being moſt ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that we ſhall not loſe thereby.</p>
                  <p>153.</p>
                  <p>Afflictions are in ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but not infallible <hi>notes</hi> of Salvation; for none ſhall be ſaved but he muſt ſuffer afflictions; but all that are afflicted ſhall not be ſaved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="190" facs="tcp:36818:99"/>154.</p>
                  <p>Wealth is not the way to heaven, but the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; let all our care be, how to live well, and then to be ſure we ſhall never dye poor.</p>
                  <p>155.</p>
                  <p>Afflictions and ſufferings are ſometimes the way to Glory in this world; <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> had never been a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, had he not firſt been a priſoner.</p>
                  <p>156.</p>
                  <p>Gods children are ever the better for being miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; <hi>It is good for me that I was afflicted:</hi> let God uſe us how he will on Earth, ſo that we may have what he
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:36818:99"/>hath promiſed to thoſe that love him in Heaven; who would not be a <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> for a day, that he might ſit in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letters">
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:36818:100"/>
                  <head>Some Heavenly Meditations, Exhortations, and Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of that bleſſed Martyr, Mr. <hi>John Bradford,</hi> and other Martyrs, written out of priſon to ſeveral Friends.</head>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>To Mr. J.H.</head>
                     <p>COnſider <hi>what this life is;</hi> Conſider <hi>what death is;</hi> Conſider <hi>what is prepared for you after death.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Concerning this life;</hi> know it is full of miſery, vanity, and wo, it is a
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:36818:100"/>plain baniſhment, and hath nothing in it that hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance; it is therefore compared to a vapour, to ſmoak, to a ſhaddow, yea to a warfare, to a vail of miſery, wherein we are compaſſed about on every ſide with moſt fierce and fearful Enemies; and ſhould we deſire to dwell there? ſhould we be fond to live in this toylſome and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious world? ſhould we wiſh to continue in this wretched eſtate? ſhould we take pleaſure to remain in this dangerous conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? <hi>Daniels</hi> den was not ſo dreadful, as is this Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon we dwell in.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="194" facs="tcp:36818:101"/>2. <hi>Concerning death;</hi> to <hi>Gods</hi> dear children what other thing is it then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcher of all diſpleaſure, the end of Travil, the door of deſires, the gate of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the port of Paradiſe, the heaven of Heaven, the entiance into reſt and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs, the path-way into Felicity, and the beginning of all bleſſedneſs. It is a very bed of Down, (and therefore compared to a ſleep) for the bodies of Gods people to reſt, out of which they ſhall ariſe, and awake moſt freſh and flouriſhing to everlaſting life. It is a paſſage to the Father, a chariot to
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:36818:101"/>Heaven, the Lords meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a leader unto Chriſt, a going to our home, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from priſon and bondage, a diſmiſſion from war, a ſecurity from all ſorrow, and a freedom from all miſery. Should we be diſmay'd at it? ſhould we be afraid of it? ſhould we trouble to hear of it? ſhould ſuch a freind as this is be unwelcome? ſhould the foulneſs of his face, fear us from his good conditions? ſhould the hardneſs of his husk, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us from his ſweet ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel? ſhould the rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Tyde tye us to the bank and ſhore?
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:36818:102"/>ſhould the hardneſs of the ſaddle ſet us on our feet to periſh by the way, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then leap up and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſame a little, and ſo to be where we would be?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Concerning that which is prepared for you after death;</hi> if I ſhould go about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it, the more I ſhould do ſo, the further I ſhould be from it. For the eye hath not ſeen, neither hath the ear heard, nor is the heart of man able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in any meaſure, the joy, mirth, melody, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, power, wealth, riches, honour, glory, wiſdom, knowledge, treaſures, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:36818:102"/>peace, quietneſs, and eternal felicity, which you ſhall enjoy world without end with God the Father, Son, and Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O! wo to our blind eyes that ſee not this, wo to the hardneſs of our hearts that feel not this, wo to the deafneſs of our ears that hear not this, in ſuch manner as we ſhould do; whereby we ſhould be ſo far from fearing death, that we ſhould rather wiſh, and deſire it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="198" facs="tcp:36818:103"/>
                     <head>To the Profeſſors of the Goſpel By Mr. <hi>John Bradford,</hi> Martyr.</head>
                     <p>IT is I Lord that have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thee, it is mine hypocriſie, my vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, my covetuouſneſs, my carnality, ſecurity, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs, unthankfulneſs, ſelf-love and ſuch like, which have deſerved the taking away of our King <hi>Edward,</hi> of thy word and true Religion, of thy good Miniſters, by exile, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and death, it is my wickedneſs that cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſucceſs and increaſe of
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:36818:103"/>authority and peace to thy Enemies.</p>
                     <p>Let us reprove the <hi>works</hi> of darkneſs, let us fly from all idolatry; let us abhor the Antichriſtian and Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh rotten ſervice, let us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the Popiſh Maſs, and forſake their Romiſh Idol, let us prepare our ſelves for the Croſs; let us be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to all in authority in things that are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his word; for then anſwer with the Apoſtle, <hi>It is better to obey God then Man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If you find and feel in your ſelves, an hope and truſt in God, that he will never tempt you above
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:36818:104"/>what he will make you able to bear; then be aſſured the Lord will be true to you, and you ſhall be able to bear all afflictions; but if you want this hope and confidence, fly and get you hence, rather then by your tarrying, Gods name ſhould be diſhonoured.</p>
                     <p>Hang on the providence of God, not only when you have means to help you, but alſo when you have no means, yea, when all means are againſt you.</p>
                     <p>Give God this honour which of all other things he chiefly and principally requireth at your hands, namely, To believe that
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:36818:104"/>you are his children <hi>through</hi> Chriſt, that he is your Father and God through him, that he loveth you, and pardoneth you all your offences, that he is with you in trouble, and will be with you for ever; that when you fall he will put under his hand, and will not let you lie long in ſin.</p>
                     <p>Let the life you lead be in the Faith of the Son of God, for <hi>the juſt doth live by Faith;</hi> which Faith flyeth from all evil, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the word of God, as a Lanthorn to her feet, and a light to her ſteps, her eyes be above where Jeſus
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:36818:105"/>Chriſt is; ſhe beholdeth not things preſent, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things to come; ſhe glorieth in afflictions, and knoweth that the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent life are not to be compared with that far more exceeding and eternal weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which God will reveal to us and in us.</p>
                     <p>Now of this glory the Lord grant us a lively taſt here, then ſhall we run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſcent that it ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth; It will make us valiant men to take to us the Kingdom of God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy bring us, in his good time, through Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="203" facs="tcp:36818:105"/>
                     <head>To Dr. H. By Mr. <hi>John Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Martyr.</head>
                     <p>SEt before your eyes the end of this ſtraight way, rather then the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſs of the paſſage; ſo doth the husbandman in plowing and tilling the ground ſet before him the harveſt time; ſo doth the Fiſherman conſider the draught of his net, rather then the caſting of it in. So doth the Merchant, the <hi>return</hi> of his Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, and ſo ſhould we in theſe ſtormy days, ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, not the loſs of
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:36818:106"/>our goods, liberty, yea of our very life, but the reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time, the coming of our ſaviour Jeſus Chriſt to judgment.</p>
                     <p>The more we loſe here, the greater joy ſhall we have in the world to come, the more we ſuffer here, the greater triumph ſhall we have there; for corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table droſs, we ſhall find incorruptable treaſure; for Gold, we ſhall have glory; for Silver, we ſhall have ſolace, and joy without meaſure; for riches, we ſhall have Royal Robes; for earthly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ouſes, we ſhall have eternal Pallaces; we ſhall there have <hi>mirth</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:36818:106"/>meaſure, pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pain, and abſolute bleſſedneſs, felicity and happineſs, without end.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>To certain of his faithful Friends, by Mr. <hi>John Bradford,</hi> Martyr.</head>
                     <p>YEe have cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce (my dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Friends) in the days of tryal and confirmation, in and by which God our Father maketh us like to the Image of Jeſus Chriſt here, that ſo we may be like unto him hereafter?</p>
                     <p>For if we ſuffer with him, we ſhall raign with
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:36818:107"/>him; if we be buried with him, we ſhall riſe with him; if we are companions with him in affliction, we ſhall rejoyce with him in glory; if we ſow with him in tears, we ſhall reap with him in joy; if we <hi>confeſs him before men, he will confeſs us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his father in heaven;</hi> if we take his part, he will take ours, if we looſe any thing for his names ſake, he will give us all things for his truth and promiſe ſake; ſo that we ought to rejoyce, and be glad, for it is not given to every one to ſuffer loſs of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, life, goods, houſe, and all things for the Lords ſake.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="207" facs="tcp:36818:107"/>What can God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do more for us, then to call us into the camp of his dear Son? what can Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour do more for us, then to make us his Warriors, and fellow Souldiers? what can the holy Ghoſt do to us above this, then to mark us with the badg and cogniſance of the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
                     <p>Be of good comfort, be of good comfort, my dear hearts in the Lord, confeſs him and his truth, and fear not the priſon, loſs of goods, or life; fear rather that priſon, out of which there is no deliverance;
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:36818:108"/>fear rather the loſs of thoſe goods which laſt for ever; fear rather the loſs of that life which is eternal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you are called, and the way by which God will bring you to it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you know not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly whether it will be by priſon, fire, or halter; whenſoever theſe come, let them not diſmay you, nor ſeem ſtrange unto you, for no ſmall number of Gods children are gone that way.</p>
                     <p>The journey is but ſhort, though unpleaſant to the fleſh; perchance if we ſhould dye in our beds by a corporal malady, it
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:36818:108"/>would be much longer and alſo more painful; but in Gods ſight it cannot be ſo precious and gainful as I know this kind of death is.</p>
                     <p>And now I commend my ſelf into the hands of my Father, by whoſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, I came into this world, by whoſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, I have been kept in this world, and by whoſe providence, I leave and depart out of this world.</p>
                     <p>Let us make our ſelves ready to ride in the fiery Chariot, leaving theſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mantles, and old Cloaks of our carcaſes behind us
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:36818:109"/>in aſhes for a little time, which God ſhall reſtore unto us again in a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>To a faithful friend of his, by Mr. <hi>John Bradford,</hi> Martyr.</head>
                     <p>BE willing to carry the Croſs of Chriſt, leaſt you carry the Croſs of the world, the fleſh, and the Devil.</p>
                     <p>One of theſe four Croſſes you muſt carry, three of them bring to hell, and therefore the greateſt part go that way, which is the broad way; only the forth
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:36818:109"/>bringeth to Heaven, but few go that way, as well becauſe the way is ſtraight, as alſo becauſe but few walk in it; how beit though it be ſtraight, it is but ſhort, and the few are many, if you conſider the godly as the Patriarks, Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Martyrs, and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and Chriſt Jeſus with all his guard and train.</p>
                     <p>Think not ſcorn to come after them who are gone before you.</p>
                     <p>I hourly look for <hi>Elias</hi> fiery Chariot to come and catch me up to Heaven; my Cloak, that is my Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, I ſhall leave behind me in aſhes, which I doubt
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:36818:110"/>not, my Lord will raiſe up; and reſtore to me again at the laſt day, glorified even like unto his moſt glorious Body. That portion of the good ſpirit which my Father hath lent me, I wiſh to be doubled, yea trebled upon you all.</p>
                     <p>If we ſuffer in the cauſe of Chriſt, our ſufferings are but ſhort, and the time of eaſe to Gods Enemies is not long, the time of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing ſhall be endleſs, but the time of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall be everlaſting and intollerable. Our break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt is ſharp, but our ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per will be ſweet. The afflictions of this life may
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:36818:110"/>not be compared in any part, with the glory that ſhall be revealed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>To his godly Friends. <hi>G.</hi> and <hi>N.</hi> By Mr. <hi>John Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Martyr.</head>
                     <p>CAſt your care on the Lord, for he careth for you; and hath coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the hairs on your head ſo that one ſhall not periſh; if you commit your ſelves to his order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereas elſe your heads and bodies, yea, and ſouls too ſhall periſh; if ye withdraw your ſelves as unwilling to take his
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:36818:111"/>Cup, and to drink of it; not that I would have you to thruſt your ſelves head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long or raſhly to pull them upon you; or that I would not have you uſe ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and lawful means as you may in the fear of God, and with a good conſcience to a void the Croſs, and give place to evil, but that I would have you willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to put forth your hand to take it when God offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, in ſuch a manner as with a good Conſcience you cannot eſcape; then take it, kiſs it, and thank God for it. It is a moſt ſure ſign that God loveth you; as he ſaith, <hi>Whom I
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:36818:111"/>love I chaſtiſe,</hi> Rev. 3.19. <hi>And if ye are not partakers of correction, ſurely ye are no children,</hi> Heb. 12.8.</p>
                     <p>But if once chaſtiſe you, and ye kiſs the rod, verily he will caſt the rod into the fire, and will imbrace you, and kiſs you as a mother doth her child, when ſhe perceiveth it to take her correction in good part.</p>
                     <p>Conſider not the things of <hi>this life</hi> (my dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved brethren) which is a very priſon to all Gods children, but the things of <hi>Everlasting life,</hi> which is our very home; but to the believing of this, you muſt open the eyes of your
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:36818:112"/>Faith, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, who ſet more by trouble with Gods people, then by the riches of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Pharoahs</hi> Court. Your houſe, home, goods, yea life, and all that ever ye have, God hath given you as love-tokens, and to admoniſh you of his love, and to win your love to him again; now he will try your love, whether you ſet more by him, then by his tokens or no. If ye for his tokens ſake, that is, for your houſe, home, goods, yea life, will go with the world, leaſt you ſhould loſe them, then be aſſured your love, as he cannot but eſpy it to be a
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:36818:112"/>Strumpets love, ſo will he reject and caſt it away with the world.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>In another Letter to the ſame perſons, by Mr. <hi>John Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Martyr.</head>
                     <p>MY dearly beloved, heavy is this anger fallen upon us all, doleful is this day. Now hath An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt gotten all his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er again, now is Chriſts Goſpel trodden under foot, now is Gods people a diviſion, and a prey for the wicked.</p>
                     <p>Now is the greateſt of all plagues fallen upon us,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:36818:113"/>the want of Gods word, and all theſe judgments we have, yea I alone have juſtly deſerved.</p>
                     <p>Oh that as I write with my hands (I alone) ſo I could wiſh <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24 17. and with <hi>Jonas</hi> in heart ſay ſo. But I do not, I do not; I ſee how grievouſly I have ſinned, and how great a miſery is fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, for my unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Gods word, for mine hypocriſy, in profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, preaching, hearing, and ſpeaking of Gods word; for my not praying to God for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it, for my not lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it throughly as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="219" facs="tcp:36818:113"/>Oh good Father, it is we that have ſinned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſerve the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of thy good word; it is we that have done amiſs, we have dealt unjuſtly with thy Goſpel, we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured thy wrath, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore juſt art thou in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing us, juſt art thou in plaguing us, for we are very miſerable.</p>
                     <p>But good Lord and dear Father of Mercies, whoſe juſtice is ſuch that thou wilt not puniſh the poor ſouls of this Realm, which yet have not thus ſinned againſt thee as we have done, (for many yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard thy word) for
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:36818:114"/>our treſpaſſes; and whoſe mercy is ſo great, that thou will put our ſins out of thy Remembrance for thy Chriſt ſake; if we believe and repent.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, let us remember that all thy deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have carried the Croſs of gracious affliction in this life, in whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany thou doſt place us, and doſt lay ſuch a Croſs upon us, as thou wilt make us able to bear, to thy glory, and our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in Chriſt, for whoſe ſake we pray thee to ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the days of this our great miſery, fallen upon us moſt juſtly, and in the
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:36818:114"/>mean ſeaſon to give us Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Repentance, Faith, and thy eternal Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Amen, Amen, Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>To Mr. <hi>J. H.</hi> and his wife, Priſoners in New-Gate.</head>
                     <p>I have heard my good Brother and Siſter, how God hath brought you both into his School-houſe of correction, he I ſay hath brought you where you are, and though your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and wit tell you it is by chance and fortune, or otherwiſe; yet my dear beloved, know for certain, that whatſoever was the
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:36818:115"/>means, God your Father was the worker hereof, and that for your good, <hi>though</hi> it may be your old <hi>Adam</hi> and poor ſences may tell you otherwiſe; yet I ſay of a truth, it is your duty to think that this Croſs is of Gods ſending, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from him, and it is out of his love and Fatherly affection, for your benefit and profit ſake.</p>
                     <p>But here perhaps you will object, <hi>what benefit, what advantage can it be?</hi> You are now kept in cloſe priſon; your children and Family are without good overſeers; and by this means your goods are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:36818:115"/>poverty will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and it may be more dangers alſo, as loſs of life, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Theſe you will ſay are no Benefits, but diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and thoſe no mean ones neither, ſo that you would be glad truly to know what benefit can come to you by this Croſs, which ſeemeth rather to bring you very great loſs and damage.</p>
                     <p>To theſe things I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that it is true indeed as you ſay, of your bodies, families, children, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, poverty, life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But if you would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:36818:116"/>a while with inward eyes, as you now behold them with outward, then perhaps you would find more eaſe.</p>
                     <p>Do you not now by <hi>your</hi> inward ſenſe perceive, that you muſt part from all theſe things, as well as with other worldly bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits; Tell me then, have you not this benefit by your Croſs, to learn to loath, and leave the world, and to long for, and deſire another world, where is perpetuity and eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
                     <p>You ought of your own mind and free will, to have forſaken the world and all
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:36818:116"/>earthly things, uſing this world as though you uſed it not, and having your hearts only ſet upon your treaſures in Heaaven, or elſe you can never be Chriſt true Diſciple, that is to be ſaved, and to be where he is.</p>
                     <p>And think you, my dear hearts in the Lord, think you that this is no benefit, to be compelled to do thus by this croſs, that ſo you may aſſuredly enjoy enleſs glory with the Lord.</p>
                     <p>How doth God now as it were fatherly correct you, to remember you of your former offences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe things, and all
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:36818:117"/>other your miſcarriages, that your repentance and remiſſion might <hi>enſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon?</hi> How doth God now compel you to call upon him, and to be earneſt in prayer? Are theſe no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits? doth not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſay, that God doth correct us in this world, becauſe we ſhould not be damned with the world? That God chaſtneth every one whom he loveth? that the end of this his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſhall be joy and holineſs? doth not the Scripture ſay, that <hi>they are happy that ſuffer for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake,</hi> as ye do, <hi>that the glory and ſpirit of God
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:36818:117"/>reſteth upon them,</hi> that <hi>as you are now made like unto Chriſt inſuffering, ſo you ſhall be made like unto him in reigning;</hi> doth not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſay, you are now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the high-way and right way to Heaven? My dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved, what greater benefit then this can a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heart deſire?</p>
                     <p>The Lord open our hearts to ſee and feel this indeed, then ſhall we think the Croſs and afflictions, which are the means to bring us to this, to be very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious; Then ſhall we thank God that he would chaſtiſe us. And that we
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:36818:118"/>may do this indeed, my dearly beloved, Let us ſtill remember that our Croſs comes from God, and that they come from God as a Father, for our profit and benefit, and therefore that we ought to call to mind our ſins, and to ask pardon for them; and to look certainly for help at Gods hand, in his good time, ſuch help as ſhall make moſt for Gods glory, and for the comfort and benefit of our ſouls eternally.</p>
                     <p>Now if we do through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe, and ſenſibly conceive theſe things, then there will iſſue out from us hearty thankſgiving,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:36818:118"/>which God requireth as a moſt precious ſacrifice.</p>
                     <p>And that we may all be thus thankful through Chriſt, let us uſe earneſt prayer to our God and dear Father, begging of him to bleſs us, keep us, and comfort us under his ſweet Croſs for ever and ever. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>To Mr. <hi>Laurence Sanders,</hi> By Mr. <hi>John Bradford,</hi> Martyr.</head>
                     <p>AH good brother, that I could alwaies have God, his majeſty, mercy, Heaven, and Hell before
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:36818:119"/>me, then ſhould I indure as <hi>Moſes,</hi> as ſeeing him that is inviſible.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord,</hi> then how much more, they that <hi>die</hi> for the Lord.</p>
                     <p>All here therefore (God be praiſed) do willingly pledg our Captain Chriſt of his Cup, even when he will, or how he will.</p>
                     <p>Let us rejoice in the ſtraight way, which few find, and fewer walk there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but feweſt of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein unto the end.</p>
                     <p>Doubting of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, is the very Dungeon of diſpair.</p>
                     <p>Who live ſoberly but ſuch as are holy?</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="231" facs="tcp:36818:119"/>Once accepted and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of God in Chriſt, and ever beloved; for whom he loveth, he loveth to the end.</p>
                     <p>Repentance and juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the Gramar School, wherein we muſt firſt be converſant and learned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we go to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Gods moſt holy predeſtination.</p>
                     <p>The pattern which we muſt follow is Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and not the multitude nor cuſtome.</p>
                     <p>In all things we muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the ſeeking of our ſelves, as well in doing, as in learning things undone.</p>
                     <p>Long did the Lord ling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:36818:120"/>and tarry to have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mercy upon us, but we were ever the longer the worſe.</p>
                     <p>He that will not have Gods bleſſing, it ſhall be taken from him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>Biſhop <hi>Ridly,</hi> In a Letter to the diſperſed brethren.</head>
                     <p>WE never had a better or more juſt cauſe, either to continue our life, or ſhed our blood; we cannot take in hand a more certain, clear, and manifeſt Truth. For it is not any ceremony for which we contend, but it toucheth
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:36818:120"/>the very ſubſtance of our whole Religion, yea even Chriſt himſelf.</p>
                     <p>What can all their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty do againſt us, but make our Crowns more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yea, beautify and multiply the ſame?</p>
                     <p>I eſteem nothing availa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for me, which will not further the glory of God.</p>
                     <p>Whoſoever knowingly neglecteth and regardeth not to keep a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he cannot have peace with God, nor a lively Faith in his mercy.</p>
                     <p>If our Doctrine were once the truth of Gods word, do you think that the alteration and change
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:36818:121"/>of the times can ever make it an untruth.</p>
                     <p>Let us joyn hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Chriſt, and if we cannot overthrow, yet over power, and as much as in us lies, let us ſhake thoſe ſtrong holds, not with carnal, but with ſpiritual weapons.</p>
                     <p>It is not the ſlanderers evil Tongue, but a mans own evil deed that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file him before God.</p>
                     <p>Yours by Gods grace in our Maſter Chriſts cauſe unto the Stake, and thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth without all dangeror peril for ever and ever.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="235" facs="tcp:36818:121"/>
                     <head>Doctor <hi>Taylor,</hi> In a Letter to Biſhop <hi>Cranmer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>GOD be praiſed again and again for this your excellent promotion, <hi>which</hi> you are called unto at this preſent, in that you are counted worthy to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed among the number of Chriſts Records, and witneſſes, <hi>England</hi> hath had but a few learned Biſhops that would ſtick to Chriſt, ſo as to burn for his cauſe.</p>
                     <p>For Gods ſake pray for us, for we fail not daily to pray for you, we are <hi>strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and ſtronger in the
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:36818:122"/>Lord, his name be praiſed, and we doubt not but ye be ſo alſo in Chriſt ſweet School; Heaven is all and wholly on our ſide.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rejoice therefore in the Lord, and again I ſay rejoyce.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pray for me, I will pray for you; God be praiſed, ſince my condemnation, I was never afraid to die.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>Biſhop <hi>Hooper</hi> In a Letter to certain godly perſons.</head>
                     <p>LEt us prav unto God ſo to furniſh us with Faith and Patience, that we may rather dye ten times, then to deny him
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:36818:122"/>once; it is very requiſite that the Members of Chriſt, comfort one another, make prayers together, confer one with another, ſo ſhall you be ſtronger, and Gods ſpirit ſhall not be abſent from you, but be in the midſt of you, to teach you, to comfort you, to make <hi>you</hi> wiſe in all godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, patient in tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſtrong in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Ye ſee how the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the wicked, by helping one another, make their wicked Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and themſelves ſtrong againſt God, his truth and his people.</p>
                     <p>If any ſmart, Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:36818:123"/>ſhall be the firſt; if any ſuffer ſhame they begin; if any be ſubject to ſlander it is thoſe that he loveth, ſo that Chriſt ſheweth no face, nor favour, nor love almoſt in this world out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to them, but doth as it were lay clay upon the ſore eyes of thoſe that are ſorrowful, yet the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient man ſeeth (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) life hid under theſe miſeries and adverſities, and light, and ſight, hid under this foul clay.</p>
                     <p>The will of our Father be done in all things, if he will life, life be it, if he will death, death be it.</p>
                     <p>It is a trouble to looſe
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:36818:123"/>the treaſures of this life, but yet a very great pain, if they be kept with offence to God; cry, call, pray, and in Chriſt daily require help, ſuccour, mercy, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, grace and defence, that the wickedneſs of this world prevail not againſt us. We began well, God preſerve us to the end.</p>
                     <p>This life is ſhort and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, happy are they that can ſpend it to the glory of God.</p>
                     <p>We may be tempted of the world, the fleſh, and the Devil, but yet although theſe things pinch, yet they do not pierce, and although they work ſin in us, yet in
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:36818:124"/>Chriſt no condemnation to them that are grafted in him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>Mr. Richard <hi>Rooth,</hi> In a Letter to certain Martyrs condemned at <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>OH dear hearts in Chriſt, what a Crown of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall ye receive with Chriſt in the Kingdome of God; Oh that it had been the good will of God that I had been ready to have gone with you, for I lie in the Biſhops little eaſe in the day, and in the <hi>night</hi> I lie in the coal-houſe, and we look every day when
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:36818:124"/>we ſhall be condemned, for they ſay, I ſhall be burned within ten days before <hi>Eaſter;</hi> but I lie ſtill at the pools brink, and every one ſtepeth in before me; but we abide patiently the Lords leiſure, in many bonds, in fetters and ſtocks, by which we have received great joy in the Lord.</p>
                     <p>Oh my dear hearts, now ſhall you be cloathed with long white garments upon mount <hi>Sion,</hi> with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Saints, and with Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour, who will never forſake us.</p>
                     <p>Oh bleſſed Virgins, you have played the wiſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins part, becauſe you have
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:36818:125"/>taken oyl into your lamps, that you may enter with the Bridegroom when he cometh into everlaſting joy. But as for the fooliſh, they ſhall be ſhut out, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they made not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ready to ſuffer with Chriſt, nor venture to take up his Croſs.</p>
                     <p>O how precious ſhall your death be in the ſight of the Lord, dear and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in his ſight is he detah of all his Saints:</hi> Farewell mine own dear Hearts, and pray the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> Pray, pray, pray.</p>
                     <p>By me <hi>Richard Rooth,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with my own blood.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="243" facs="tcp:36818:125"/>
                     <head>Mr. <hi>John Philpot,</hi> In a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Mr. <hi>R.H.R.G.M.H.</hi> and <hi>J.C.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>GLorious is the courſe of the Martyrs at this day; Never had the Elect of God a better time for their glory then this is. Now may they be aſſured under the Croſs that they are Chriſts Diſciples for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
                     <p>Many go on well, till they come to the Pikes, and then they turn their backs, and give over in the plain field, to the ſhame of Chriſt and his Church, that
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:36818:126"/>hath ſo faint hearted Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in his camp at the time of need, in that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his glory ought moſt manfully to be ſhewed.</p>
                     <p>Be content to have your Faith tryed every day by ſome Croſs or other, as it pleaſeth God to put it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and if God put no grievous Croſs upon you, let your brethrens Croſs be your Croſs, which is a certain token of true brotherly love.</p>
                     <p>Hitherto we have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted unto blood-ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, our blood muſt not be too dear for the Lord, and then his Kingdome ſhall not be too dear for us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="245" facs="tcp:36818:126"/>We have taken our Preſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony a great while, let us now learn to ſerve him faithfully, and not to fly out of the Lords camp into the world, as many do.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>Mr. <hi>John Careleſs,</hi> To ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Martyrs condemned to die for the truth, in New-Gate.</head>
                     <p>SO great honour is not permitted to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Angel in Heaven, as to ſuffer for the name of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Full glad may you be that ever God gave you a life to loſe for his ſake.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="246" facs="tcp:36818:127"/>A weak Faith hath ever a cold charity annexed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, which is quenched with every unkind word.</p>
                     <p>Nothing can anger the malicious mind, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered heart of Satan more, then the mirth, gladneſs, and hearty rejoycing of Gods Children in their good Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Only Chriſts true Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples do mourn for his abſence, therefore they ſhall doubtleſs rejoyce in his preſence, which will be ſo much the more joyful, by how much the more his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is ſorrowful.</p>
                     <p>According to your Faith and as you believe, ſo ſhall
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:36818:127"/>it be unto you, and as you think God to be unto you, ſuch a one you ſhall find him to be, think there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever ſweetly of the Lord, and of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>Mr. <hi>John Careleſs</hi> In a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Mr. <hi>John Bradford.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NOw with a merry heart, and joyful tears, I take my farewel of you, mine own dear bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Lord, begging him to ſend us ſhortly a joyful meeting in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that we may both ſing praiſes together unto
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:36818:128"/>him with his holy Angels, and bleſſed ſpirits for ever and ever.</p>
                     <p>Farewel thou bleſſed of the Lord, farewel in Chriſt, depart unto thy reſt, and pray for me for Gods ſake.</p>
                     <p>Well, I will hope in God, and pray all night that God would ſend me ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to morrow, and if the Lord give you leaſure to morrow, let me hear four words of comfort from you for Gods ſake.</p>
                     <p>Oh that my life, and a thouſand ſuch wretched lives more might go for yours. Oh why doth God ſuffer me, and ſuch other poor worms to live, that
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:36818:128"/>can do nothing but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Alms of the Church, and yet take you away ſo worthy a work-man and Labourer in the Lords vineyard?</p>
                     <p>But wo be to our ſins and great unthankfulneſs which is the cauſe of tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away of ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord, as ſhould ſet forth his glory, and inſtruct his people; if we had been thankful to God for the good Miniſters of his word, we had not been ſo ſoon deprived of them; The Lord forgive our great ingratitude and his, and give us true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and faith, and
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:36818:129"/>ſtretch forth his hand of mercy over us, for his dear Son Chriſt his ſake; take not away all thy true Preachers out of this Realm O Lord, but leave us a ſeed, leaſt <hi>England</hi> be made as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> when thy true <hi>Lots</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and gone.</p>
                     <p>But why go I about to mingle your mirth with my mourning, your juſt <hi>joy</hi> with my deſerved ſorrow? if I loved you as I pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I ſhould ſurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice with you moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and praiſe God from the very bottom of my heart; I ſhould praiſe God night and day for your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:36818:129"/>Election, in and through his great mercy.</p>
                     <p>I ſhould give him moſt humble thanks for your vocation by his Goſpel, and your true knowledg in the ſame.</p>
                     <p>I ſhould earneſtly praiſe him for your ſweet juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, whereof you are moſt certain by Gods grace and ſpirit; I ſhould earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray to him for your Glorification, which ſhall ſhortly enſue.</p>
                     <p>I ſhould rejoice and be glad to ſee you dignified by the Crown of <hi>Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and to be appointed to that honour to teſtifie his truth, and to ſeal it
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:36818:130"/>with your blood.</p>
                     <p>I ſhould highly extol the Lord, who hath given you a glorious victory over all your Enemies, viſible and inviſible, and hath given <hi>you</hi> grace and ſtrength to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your Courſe as you have begun.</p>
                     <p>Oh that the time were now come, that I might put off this frail Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the fleſh, in this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſecurity, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of conſcience in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Yours for ever in the Lord Jeſus,</hi> John Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, <hi>living in hope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hope</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="253" facs="tcp:36818:130"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> John Careleſs, <hi>to Mr.</hi> Philpot.</head>
                     <p>MY dearly beloved <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> God hath <hi>brought</hi> you into a ſtraight place; out of your pinching and painful ſeat in priſon, you have plentifully poured up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me your precious Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſweet Savour whereof hath greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed my faint and tired ſoul.</p>
                     <p>Ah good <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> hath <hi>Paſhur</hi> put <hi>thee</hi> in the <hi>Stocks?</hi> why, now thou haſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of a Prophet, thy glory never began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear until now.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="254" facs="tcp:36818:131"/>Oh good Mr. <hi>Philpot,</hi> which art a principle <hi>Pot</hi> indeed, filled with moſt precious liquor, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by thy plenteous pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out of the ſame; O <hi>Pot</hi> moſt happy, ordained to honour by the high <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> thou doſt contain hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly treaſure in thy earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en veſſel. Oh <hi>Pot</hi> thrice hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, in whom Chriſt hath wrought a great miracle, altering thy nature, and turning water into Wine, and that of the beſt, out of whom the Maſter of the Feaſt hath filled my cup ſo full, that I am even o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome in joy of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit through the ſame.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="255" facs="tcp:36818:131"/>Be not offended, dear heart, at my Metaphorical ſpeech, for I am diſpoſed to be merry, and with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> to dance before the Ark of the Lord, and though you play on a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful pair of Organs, the Stocks, not very comly, nor eaſie to the fleſh, yet the ſweet ſound that came from thence to me, from you, cauſeth me thus to ſpeak.</p>
                     <p>Oh that I were with you in the body (as I am preſent in ſpirit) that I might ſing all care away in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our bleſſed Saviour and <hi>Redeemer</hi> from all trouble, for now the time of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is come.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="256" facs="tcp:36818:132"/>
                     <head>Mr. <hi>Laurence Sanders,</hi> In a Letter to the true Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Goſpel.</head>
                     <p>MY dear friends in the Lord, the times are perilous and dangerous, we muſt therefore be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect and not ſolace, &amp; delight our ſelves in carnal ſecurity, but with a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and contented mind we muſt now venture into the ſhip of Chriſts Croſs and afflictions; and now let us ſeriouſly weigh, and conſider, all the perils, dangers, and hazards that we muſt expect to meet
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:36818:132"/>in our journey to our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Countrey, yet let us account it comfort e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in this dangerous Voyage, that we have the company and fellowſhip of ſuch an adventurer as our bleſſed Lord Jeſus to go along with us; when he was once in the ſhip with his Diſciples, with his word he did aſſwage the ſwelling of the dangerous Seas, and he hath not left us alone in this ſhip, either to ſink or to ſwim, but will be awaked, if he be call'd upon by importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate prayer.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb n="258" facs="tcp:36818:133"/>
                  <head>Holy Breathings: OR, A Divine Dialogue between <hi>Jeſus</hi> and the <hi>Soul. <hi>With other Poems.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat. 11.28.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>COme unto me;</hi> what voice is this I here?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="259" facs="tcp:36818:133"/>
                     <speaker>Ieſus.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It is the ſweet voice of thy Saviour dear,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He calleth labouring ſinners, to him flee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He calleth laden ſinners, ſuch as thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He calleth ſinners, bids them come away,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He calleth all, Oh why then ſhouldſt thou ſtay?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He calleth ſuch as by ſin are undone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He calleth thee, therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him run.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                     <l>But how I ſhould come to thee <hi>Bleſſed Lord,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sin</hi> is the only thing by thee abhord.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="260" facs="tcp:36818:134"/>And I am nothing elſe but <hi>ſin,</hi> and thou,</l>
                     <l>Wilt not of <hi>ſin,</hi> of the leaſt <hi>ſin</hi> allow;</l>
                     <l>Beſides thou art in heaven, and how ſhall I,</l>
                     <l>Reach unto thee, thou art above the sky?</l>
                     <l>And I poor creature, grov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the earth,</l>
                     <l>The mold from which at firſt I came by birth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ieſus.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Remember ſoul my bleſſed word that ſaith,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That coming to me, is alone by Faith.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou Lord that putteſt faith into mans heart,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="261" facs="tcp:36818:134"/>Beſtow on me that gift; to me impart</l>
                     <l>Such other graces as may let me ſee</l>
                     <l>My want of Chriſt, that I may come to thee.</l>
                     <l>My ſins thou know'ſt a heavy burden are,</l>
                     <l>A load that is too big for me to bear.</l>
                     <l>No ſlave that's under Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Tyranny,</l>
                     <l>Is under ſuch ſad bondage as am I.</l>
                     <l>But it is unto thee O Chriſt I come,</l>
                     <l>Believing in thee; Oh make me a Room</l>
                     <l>Within thy Arms, take me into thy heart,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="262" facs="tcp:36818:135"/>And ſince my <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>weak, ſtrong Faith</hi> impart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ieſus.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Poor Soul! take comfort, though thy Faith be ſmall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A grain of muſtard ſeed's ſmalleſt of all.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet I of muſtard ſeeds of Faith allow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So that thy Soul unto my Scepter bow.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nay of one grain; a wonder let it be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To thy poor ſoul that ſuch love is in me:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That I accept of Faith, even of the leaſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That I receive ſo poor, ſo vile a gueſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As wretched man, who nothing hath to bring,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="263" facs="tcp:36818:135"/>
                        <hi>To make him acceptable but his ſin.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                     <l>O bleſſed Jeſus! mount me on the wing</l>
                     <l>Of Holy Faith; let me not feel the ſting</l>
                     <l>Of conſcience; but let me anſwer all</l>
                     <l>That I believed, and went at Chriſt his call.</l>
                     <l>My Saviour call'd, and I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him went,</l>
                     <l>He gave me Faith, and helpt me to repent.</l>
                     <l>I come with ſorrow, that I ſinned have,</l>
                     <l>I come with Faith, that thou my ſoul wilt ſave.</l>
                     <l>It is but weak, O Lord, I muſt confeſs,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="264" facs="tcp:36818:136"/>It is a feeble hand, yet ne're the leſs,</l>
                     <l>It is the hand of Faith, and it is true,</l>
                     <l>It lays holds on <hi>thee,</hi> claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but its due,</l>
                     <l>And that is <hi>Reſt,</hi> which thou haſt promiſed me,</l>
                     <l>And my poor ſoul is <hi>reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> till with thee.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reſt</hi> is that good all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do deſire;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reſt</hi> is that good, to which all Saints aſpire.</l>
                     <l>If th' bodies <hi>resting</hi> after labour be,</l>
                     <l>So ſweet, ſo pleaſant, as we know, and ſee,</l>
                     <l>Then what is it to have the ſoul to <hi>reſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="265" facs="tcp:36818:136"/>In the enjoyment of a God ſtill bleſt.</l>
                     <l>From thee is all the <hi>reſt</hi> for which I look,</l>
                     <l>For it is written in thy ſacred book,</l>
                     <l>That thoſe that caſt, and roul themſelves on thee,</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt receive; O Lord receive thou me.</l>
                     <l>For ſtill this Prayer, I will pray, (though brief,)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lord I believe, Lord help my unbelief.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou art now mine by faith, I thine by love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From this perſwaſion let me never move.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="266" facs="tcp:36818:137"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Oh that my ways were directed to keep thy Statutes,</q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal: 119.5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </epigraph>
                  <lg>
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <l>O That I could <hi>ſtand firm</hi> at laſt,</l>
                     <l>And not be <hi>reeling</hi> too and fro!</l>
                     <l>O that I could <hi>my God hold faſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And never, never, let him go!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>How often do I go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray,</l>
                     <l>And leave my reſt, my wonted bliſs?</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="267" facs="tcp:36818:137"/>Like a loſt ſheep in the High-way,</l>
                     <l>Which dangerous and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren is.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>I have no pleaſure in my ſin,</l>
                     <l>And yet I Act it o're and o're!</l>
                     <l>I'm ſtill the ſame that I have been,</l>
                     <l>Though fain I would be ſo no more.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>I long to keep the Law of God,</l>
                     <l>But ſtill I break it to my pain,</l>
                     <l>My ſtomach ſerves to take that food,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="268" facs="tcp:36818:138"/>But ſtraight I caſt it up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <l>My God! O take me unto thee,</l>
                     <l>With fire hot zeal melt thou my heart,</l>
                     <l>That now I may new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moulded be,</l>
                     <l>And made ſound in my better part.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <l>Lord lead me by thy grace, that I</l>
                     <l>May never wander from thee more,</l>
                     <l>Thou art my life, I cannot die,</l>
                     <l>Thou art my all, I can't be poor.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="269" facs="tcp:36818:138"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>I ſee another Law in my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, warring againſt the Law of my mind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <bibl>Rom. <hi>7.23.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </epigraph>
                  <l>WRetch that I am! my wiſhes are my pain,</l>
                  <l>Two Laws ſo different, rend my heart in twain.</l>
                  <l>My heart divided, bleeds in either part!</l>
                  <l>Offending either Law, I'm ſure to ſmart!</l>
                  <l>Inſlav'd to ſin, I'm forc'd to bear this yoke.</l>
                  <l>I kiſs the rod, ev'n whilſt I feel the ſtroak.</l>
                  <l>The ingrateful <hi>ſerpent</hi> in my breſt I warm!</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="270" facs="tcp:36818:139"/>How I drink poyſon, and imbrace my harm.</l>
                  <l>My pleaſure is my trouble, and the heat</l>
                  <l>Of fond deſire, what is't but a cold ſweat?</l>
                  <l>Alas! I'm taken with the baits of Sin!</l>
                  <l>Thoſe corrupt joyes but feed the worm within;</l>
                  <l>I triumph when my heart me pris'ner takes,</l>
                  <l>My minde is griev'd thus at the ſpoil it makes.</l>
                  <l>O Jeſus for me wounded! ſee my wound!</l>
                  <l>Give me thy Bruiſes, that I may be ſound!</l>
                  <l>With thy blood waſh my heart, in blood imbru'd!</l>
                  <l>Give me that peace, which may this War conclude.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="271" facs="tcp:36818:139"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Help thou my unbelief,</q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mark 9.24.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </epigraph>
                  <l>HElp Maſter of my faith! I'm forc't to wink</l>
                  <l>At this bright truth! in theſe great depths I ſink!</l>
                  <l>O 'tis beyond my reach, I cannot tread,</l>
                  <l>Nor can I ſwim unleſs thou hold my head!</l>
                  <l>My reaſons at a ſtand, thus are thy ways</l>
                  <l>Paſt finding out! How daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are thy rays</l>
                  <l>O Sun of righteouſneſs, to humane ſight,</l>
                  <l>Thou art ſo glorious, I can't ſee for light.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="272" facs="tcp:36818:140"/>My <hi>joys</hi> are <hi>chang'd</hi> to <hi>doubts,</hi> and <hi>fears,</hi> which roul</l>
                  <l>Like ſtormy billows in my wavering ſoul!</l>
                  <l>Shine forth my Son, amidſt theſe ſhowers of tears,</l>
                  <l>Let thy clear beams pierce <hi>through theſe cloud</hi> of <hi>fears.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shew me thy hidden <hi>Mauna,</hi> Angels food,</l>
                  <l>I long to taſt, and ſee that thou art good.</l>
                  <l>I'm come to ſee the Lord, though vile and poor,</l>
                  <l>O let me in; I'le die elſe at thy door.</l>
                  <l>Oh Lord reſtore me to thy Grace,</l>
                  <l>I hope thou doſt but hide thy face.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="273" facs="tcp:36818:140"/>O Jeſus do but look on me,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Peter,</hi> I'le weep bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly.</l>
                  <l>By thy bright face ſhew me my ſtain,</l>
                  <l>I'le pour forth tears to waſh it clean.</l>
                  <l>I hope the day will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain anon,</l>
                  <l>The Sun of Righteouſneſs is ſet, not gone.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="274" facs="tcp:36818:141"/>
                  <head>Having the Loyns of your mind girded.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THere is a God! my ſoul how durſt thou ſtray?</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt meet his vengeance if thou go this way.</l>
                     <l>Return, Return, Lo this path ſeems too broad,</l>
                     <l>Here many go, the way to heaven's, no road.</l>
                     <l>My ſoul put on thy Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, gird them faſt,</l>
                     <l>'Twill make thee comely thus to go ſtraight-lac't.</l>
                     <l>And now I am reſolv'd in ſpight of Hell,</l>
                     <l>And my falſe Heart; I'ie ſtill ſtrive to do well.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="275" facs="tcp:36818:141"/>In all my warfare, I'le hold faſt my ſhield,</l>
                     <l>Then Satan do thy worſt, I'le win the field.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>A Farewel to the World.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <l>FAlſ-hearted world; fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, farewel, I find, thee too unkind.</l>
                     <l>I took thee for a friend, did love to play, with thee all day.</l>
                     <l>But thou didſt cheat me ſtill I to my ſhame loſt every game.</l>
                     <l>Thy ſtakes were pleaſures and deceitful toies,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="276" facs="tcp:36818:142"/>Mine were true coyn, full weight, large ſolid joys.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>Now thou haſt got all that I had, I ſee Thou ſlighteſt me.</l>
                     <l>Thou uſed'ſt to imbrace me kindly, and give me thy hand.</l>
                     <l>With many promiſes of love, but lo, Thou art my foe.</l>
                     <l>Though all my ſerious thoughts and company</l>
                     <l>(Fool that I was) I left to follow thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>But I'le return to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; I'le rome no more from home.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="277" facs="tcp:36818:142"/>The mind that ſtays within ſhall ne're complain, of Wind, or Rain,</l>
                     <l>Of care, or greif, for ſtorms ſhake only breaſts that ſeek their reſts</l>
                     <l>Without doors; where is nought but toile, as <hi>though</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To be kept warm, they'd lie in beds of ſnow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>Great God, I leave the <hi>world</hi> and come to thee, open to me,</l>
                     <l>I call! O let me find thy throne of grace, I ſeek thy face,</l>
                     <l>I'le die to ſin, put off my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and then, be born agen.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="278" facs="tcp:36818:143"/>Chriſts blood ſhall be my life; the word (that can</l>
                     <l>Call up the Dead) is breath to the new Man.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:36818:143"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Nath. Crouch.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Soundhearted Chriſtian, or a diſcourſe of ſincerity, with ſeveral other Sermons, by <hi>W. Greenhil</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> Price <hi>as.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The freeneſs of the grace and love of God to believers, in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sermons, by <hi>W. Bridg,</hi> late Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter at <hi>Yormouth,</hi> price 1<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The evil Tongue tryed and found guilty, or a diſcourſe againſt backbiting and defaiming, by S. <hi>Ford</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>London</hi> price 1<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Eternal Glorification begun in Regeneration, by S. <hi>Ford,</hi> price 1s. 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> body of Divinity, or the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſtianity, both as to
<pb facs="tcp:36818:144"/>faith and practice, by <hi>T. Collier</hi> of the weſt of England, price 4s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, or the devout ſouls aſcention to heaven in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Thankſgivings and praiſes, with Sculptures, by <hi>Jo. Hall B.D.</hi> price 1 s.</item>
               <item>A Guide to eternal glory, or brief directions to all Chriſtians, how to obtain a Saving intereſt in Chriſt, in order to their everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſalvation, price 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Compleat Engliſh Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in Spelling, Reading and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, teaching Children or others to ſpell and read exactly, with pictures, price 1 s.</item>
               <item>A Journey to Jeruſalem, or the Travels of 14 Engliſh men in the year 1669 to Jeruſalem, price 1s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Otto Techenius</hi> his <hi>Hippocrates Chymicus,</hi> with his <hi>Clavis,</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Engliſh by <hi>J.W.</hi> price 5 s.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36818:144"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
